<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>🌞 Araw Seekers 🌞</title>
    <link>/authors/ohio/</link>
    <description>Recent content on 🌞 Araw Seekers 🌞</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>Isya and Ohio</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 16 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/authors/ohio/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>One Year Since Quitting Facebook</title>
      <link>/posts/fbless/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 16 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/fbless/</guid>
      <description>Another excuse to binge on social media  Use of FB in daily lives Since it&amp;rsquo;s free to sign up and use its services, Facebook has been popular for many Filipinos from all walks of life. Here they get updates from friends and non-friends, from relatives, from celebrities, and even from the news. It has become its own social news aggregate. Users provide the data, such as date of birth, school last attended, the things they like or don&amp;rsquo;t like, etc.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>That Week We Stayed at Bohol</title>
      <link>/posts/bohol/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 29 Nov 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/bohol/</guid>
      <description>First Day, 22 Nov A short intro to a long travel to airport The day started with the perennial traffic. If you&amp;rsquo;re from Metro Manila, of course, a day of commute starts there. It&amp;rsquo;s not that we didn&amp;rsquo;t almost make it on time to the airport, it&amp;rsquo;s just that we weren&amp;rsquo;t expecting a bad traffic jam on a non-rush hour, but hey, why are we even surprised?
We did make it, though, on time - enough time, even, to have a quick lunch comprising unpalatable highway robbery airport food.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Plants as Trash Deterrent?</title>
      <link>/posts/plants-deterrent/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/plants-deterrent/</guid>
      <description>A staple in both landscaping and urban planning is adding a natural element in an otherwise human-made environment. Depending on the budget, it could be a fountain to provide a water element; or it could be as simple as adding plants along sidewalks. In places all over, we have seen good and bad implementations of these natural elements, but the most common perhaps is the latter — plants.
Exhibit A People have concluded that this plant box (and many others) is where to place their trash.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Many days meshing into a manifesto (of sorts)</title>
      <link>/posts/manifesto/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 19 Aug 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/manifesto/</guid>
      <description>THE FACTUAL PIECES here shall be made obvious when necessary, so try to make allowances for every entry. They say that when two opposite states of matter coexist at a single point in time, it&amp;rsquo;s believed to be in superposition unless an observer finds themself literate enough of the ways to approach such nuance. Accordingly, these statements are neither true nor false until someone (you, the observer?) comes along, and formulates a theory that we can together test.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Taiwan Trip, June 2019, (Part 2 of 2)</title>
      <link>/posts/taiwan-part2/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 28 Jul 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/taiwan-part2/</guid>
      <description>Have you read Part 1?
Day 3 We ate breakfast in McDo, the one near the place we stayed in, and it didn’t serve any local variant of Taiwan&amp;rsquo;s food. It&amp;rsquo;s all hamburgers, fried chicken, and sausage McNothin’. Some would say that eating at a known (read: exploitive capitalist) fast food chain, one that you also have in your country, is a disservice to the self to get to know the locals or their food, but that wasn’t our case.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Taiwan Trip, June 2019, (Part 1 of 2)</title>
      <link>/posts/taiwan-part1/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 21 Jul 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/taiwan-part1/</guid>
      <description>5W, 1H of it The last week of October 2018, Gab (Isya’s sister) and Merci (Isya’s mother) went to Taipei, Taiwan to attend Gab’s first international group exhibit. Aside from that, they took the trip as a break from their usual routines in Manila and Dumaguete.
Their five-day stay in Taipei, Taiwan did not bring any actual “pasalubong” or take-home gifts, but they had a lot of stories and memorable experiences to share with us, me and Ohio.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Imperfect Narrative of Repairing an iPod Classic 160GB</title>
      <link>/posts/repair-ipod/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Jul 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/repair-ipod/</guid>
      <description>It is well known in practice that repair of a failed item may not yield a functioning item which is &amp;ldquo;as good as new.&amp;rdquo; Brown, Mark, and Frank Proschan. &amp;ldquo;Imperfect repair.&amp;quot; Journal of Applied probability 20.4 (1983): 851-859.
 In our opinion, repairing broken things is a noble undertaking for anyone who is looking to reduce the waste we send to our landfills. In this world filled with people who breaks things, a repair-person is in demand, nay, GOLD.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>