<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <channel>
        <title>Posts on ðŸŒž Araw Seekers ðŸŒž</title>
        <link>/posts/</link>
        <description>Recent content in Posts on ðŸŒž Araw Seekers ðŸŒž</description>
        <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
        <language>en-us</language>
        <copyright>Isya and Ohio</copyright>
        <lastBuildDate>Sun, 30 Aug 2020 14:53:26 +0800</lastBuildDate>
        <atom:link href="/posts/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
        
        <item>
            <title>One Year Since Quitting Facebook</title>
            <link>/posts/fbless/</link>
            <pubDate>Sun, 16 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            
            <guid>/posts/fbless/</guid>
            <description>Another excuse to binge on social media  Use of FB in daily lives Since it&amp;rsquo;s free to sign up and use its services, Facebook has been popular for many Filipinos from all walks of life. Here they get updates from friends and non-friends, from relatives, from celebrities, and even from the news. It has become its own social news aggregate. Users provide the data, such as date of birth, school last attended, the things they like or don&amp;rsquo;t like, etc.</description>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[
    <figure class="center" >
        <img src="/images/facebook.jpeg"  alt="A laptop showing a photo of cat in a Facebook group"   style="border-radius: 8px; max-width:100%;height:auto;"  />

        
            <figcaption class="center"  style="color: 297298;" >Another excuse to binge on social media</figcaption>
        
    </figure>


<h2 id="use-of-fb-in-daily-lives">Use of FB in daily lives</h2>
<p>Since it&rsquo;s free to sign up and use its services, Facebook has been popular for many Filipinos from all walks of life. Here they get updates from friends and non-friends, from relatives,  from celebrities, and even from the news. It has become its own social news aggregate. Users provide the data, such as date of birth, school last attended, the things they like or don&rsquo;t like, etc.; and these data are then fed to the platform&rsquo;s algorithm that&rsquo;s being tweaked to better serve you, i.e, show you things you might appreciate.</p>
<p>As far as we know, the telecom providers here in the Philippines provide free data to FB users. This is useful, especially with the Messenger, in which one can send and receive virtually unlimited number of messages to and from their friends and family, without having to worry about data charges. There are limitations, of course, when using only free data. For example, photos and videos are not outright available. Still, Facebook, and its other services, Instagram and WhatsApp, seems to be the practical choice when connecting to people with smartphones nowadays.</p>
<h2 id="why-quit-fb">Why Quit FB</h2>
<p>Knowing the practical uses of FB, why then do we recommend on quitting the platform altogether?</p>
<p>Because when it mishandled <a href="https://www.reuters.com/article/us-facebook-privacy-idUSKCN1HB2CM">some 87 million personally identifiable information</a>, we should now suspect that it&rsquo;s not the best platform out there to trust our data with. Also, <a href="https://www.techrepublic.com/article/facebook-data-privacy-scandal-a-cheat-sheet/">Facebook has been acting up</a>, not a behavior of a company we like to support.</p>
<p>There&rsquo;s also a more important notion that quitting FB predicates, and that is quitting Social Media completely. While there are many social networking sites, FB and its subsidiaries hold the most clout, Twitter following closely behind, at least outside China.</p>
<p>Social media has become the gateway to promote the lifestyles we can&rsquo;t afford. We actively engage in it for fear of missing out. Until we realize that use of our Time is the most distant concept from Free, we will continue expressing ourselves in platforms like Facebook, expecting validation from people.</p>
<h3 id="the-process">The Process</h3>
<p>There are many tutorials out there that detail the exact way of deactivating and permanently deleting your FB account, but we like the <a href="https://www.wikihow.com/Quit-Facebook">WikiHow</a> the best.</p>
<p>Once deactivated, you still need to wait for 30 days of &ldquo;probation&rdquo; period before FB would finally take down your profile from the platform. The &ldquo;probation&rdquo; period is mostly to test if you really want to quit. We don&rsquo;t know for sure, however, if they would keep records of your data even after &ldquo;taking them down&rdquo;. Knowing FB, though, it&rsquo;s best assumed that they would. During the wait, be sure to resist the urge to log back in, as this would only reactivate your account, and reset the 30-day count.</p>
<h3 id="the-argument-for-how-to-contact-family--friends">The Argument for How to Contact Family &amp; Friends</h3>
<p>We recommend instant messaging apps that support end-to-end encryption (E2EE), which is &ldquo;a system of communication where the only people who can read the messages are the people communicating,&rdquo; according to this <a href="https://www.wired.com/2014/11/hacker-lexicon-end-to-end-encryption/">Wired article</a>.</p>
<p><a href="https://www.privacytools.io">PrivacyTools</a> lists the recommended apps for this, and we the Araw Seekers choose the <a href="https://www.signal.org">Signal Messenger</a> for its intuitive UI and accessibility for non-hardcore privacy enthusiasts.</p>
<p>If you must still be in social media (hey, no judgement from us), PrivacyTools also has a list of decentralized social networks, which you can check out <a href="https://www.privacytools.io/providers/social-networks/">here</a>.</p>
<h2 id="but-how-can-i-quit-when-life-is-boring">&ldquo;But how can I quit when life is boring?&rdquo;</h2>
<p>Modern technology has provided us many things in life. Now, information is accessible to us 24/7. The dopamine hit when we encounter a novel information is worth noting, since it&rsquo;s one of the main reasons of social media addiction.</p>
<h3 id="its-okay-to-not-enjoy-every-moment">It&rsquo;s okay to not enjoy every moment.</h3>
<p>It&rsquo;s okay to be bored. The next time it happens, observe yourself what happens when you let boredom be. What does it feel like? Can it be so intimidating that you&rsquo;d let it win by eradicating it? Paradoxical, it sounds like, and that&rsquo;s what happens every time you fill your mind with posts from social media.</p>
<p>If you stay still for a while, it can lead to introspection that you may have never done in a long while. Soon, things surface from this boredom: you hear the sounds of nature; you feel your body itching; you begin to see the details that you didn&rsquo;t notice before. And yet we are quick to label them unexciting. Why so? We argue that paying attention to yourself, to other people, and to your surroundings outside the digital space, and especially outside social media, leads to more interesting discoveries that in turn become more nourishing when such connections are made to flourish.</p>
<p>And don&rsquo;t take it from us. One study suggest that &ldquo;<a href="https://journals.aom.org/doi/abs/10.5465/amd.2017.0033">boredom increases creativity</a>.&rdquo; However, such is applicable only to &ldquo;individuals with a high learning goal orientation, high need for cognition, high openness to experience, and high internal locus of control, suggesting that boredom motivates individuals to engage in novelty-seeking responses.&rdquo;</p>
<h3 id="what-to-do-with-the-free-hours-or-the-novelty-seeking-responses">What to do with the free hours (or, The Novelty-Seeking Responses)</h3>
<p>When you finally bid FB good riddance, what do you do with this newfound free time?</p>
<p>The most obvious would be to pick up one or two hobbies, although two would be better: one physical, one mental. For example, you could start doing short runs (physical), while learning a new language (mental). You can kick start both of these with minimal expense on your end.</p>
<p>If you&rsquo;d like to stick a routine, consider:</p>
<ul>
<li>doing housework, clean up your room, cook lunch, buy groceries;</li>
<li>or, if you are done with those, study and learn something new (a language, a skill);</li>
<li>or, if you are done with that for the day, call friends, meet up and be around people, familiar or new;</li>
<li>or, if you have already met them, go for a walk outside, explore the neighborhood;</li>
<li>or, if it&rsquo;s rainy, read a book, watch a movie;</li>
<li>or, if you already did that, listen to music, but focus on it and don&rsquo;t dismiss it on the background;</li>
<li>or, you have heard already all the albums, practice playing a few songs on the guitar (or any music instrument);</li>
<li>or, if you already did that, take a nap, write something on your journal and reflect, meditate;</li>
<li>or, you know, you could use some shower.</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="personal-opinions-of-having-and-not-having-facebook">Personal opinions of having and not having Facebook</h2>
<h3 id="isya-has-fb-as-she-tells-it">Isya has FB (as she tells it)</h3>
<h4 id="pros">Pros</h4>
<p>Facebook has enabled cheap, fast, and reliable means of communication for families who are continents apart to stay connected with each other.</p>
<h4 id="cons">Cons</h4>
<p>Since the FB&rsquo;s UI/UX (user interface and user experience, respectively, both are closely intertwined) is designed to keep its users&rsquo; attention on the platform for as long as possible (e.g. by infinite scrolling and/or news feed tailored to the user&rsquo;s behavior), it can be time consuming. As a marketing tool, this is necessary: the longer you are on FB, the more exposed you are to the many advertisements. What if we spent these X amount of hours in more meaningful activities?</p>
<p>Another important question we should ask ourselves is, &ldquo;Are we still talking to each other?&rdquo; Meaning, do our connections in the platform have any meaning to our lives? Or does Facebook, as well as other major social media platforms, simply create FOMO, eventually leading to emotional exhaustion?</p>
<h3 id="ohio-has-no-fb-as-he-tells-it">Ohio has no FB (as he tells it)</h3>
<h4 id="pros-1">Pros</h4>
<p>I am no longer subjected to news, which have now spilled over to Facebook for visibility. While staying informed is needed in order to function in society (however that goes), news, as it is presented by mainstream media, do not benefit me in any way. If anything, it only worsens my mood, given that they are rarely structured to be just facts. It&rsquo;s laid out to stir the most emotions. In doing so increases the engagement.</p>
<p>I don&rsquo;t need to focus on them, as I only have control over two things, really: what I think and what I do. All else is beyond me. Problems come in once I start trying to control the external forces.</p>
<p>I know that this mindset isn&rsquo;t for everyone, but this is what helped me to quit FB, and to be honest, it has freed me from certain anxieties that only exposure to social media can cause.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Staying informed&rdquo; becomes an excuse to check in regularly, a bad trip that the media exploits to make me dig in more into the rabbit hole.</p>
<h4 id="cons-1">Cons</h4>
<p>Since a lot of peoples &ndash; from creatives to corporations, politicians to propagandists, and everyone in between &ndash; rely now on social media for PR (public relations and/or press release), I am missing the latest happenings around me. But I don&rsquo;t see this as a big con. Instead, this <a href="https://books.google.com.ph/books?id=Dk6XDwAAQBAJ&amp;lpg=PT6&amp;ots=VHzNmBHxxy&amp;dq=joy%20of%20missing%20out&amp;lr&amp;pg=PT11#v=onepage&amp;q=joy%20of%20missing%20out&amp;f=false">joy of missing out</a> (&quot;<a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/happiness-is-state-mind/201807/jomo-the-joy-missing-out">the emotional intelligence that makes you present and content with where you are at life</a>&quot;) lets me focus on other things that I find more fulfilling to accomplish. And anyway, if the news becomes so relevant, there&rsquo;s no escaping it: people around me will talk more often about it, and soon enough, it will have reached me organically by word of mouth.</p>
<p>And yet, I cannot rely on word of mouth alone, especially when it comes to real-time communication. Free FB data bridges this spacetime gap between family and friends. Since I have none, I&rsquo;m out of the loop.</p>
<p>Then, they will come around and ask me why I did it. I&rsquo;m not always able to answer, or, if i do, not phrase it understandably. And the inquirers will leave unconvinced.</p>
<h2 id="alternatives">Alternatives&hellip;?</h2>
<h3 id="linkedin-profile">Linkedin Profile</h3>

    <figure class="center" >
        <img src="/images/linkedin.jpeg"  alt="A laptop showing a feed from LinkedIn"   style="border-radius: 8px; max-width:100%;height:auto;"  />

        
            <figcaption class="center"  style="color: 297298;" >It&#39;s okay to dislike your job by pretending you agree with colleagues.</figcaption>
        
    </figure>


<p>In the age of information, it&rsquo;s become an unwritten rule to have an online presence. While we believe that this shouldn&rsquo;t be the case, the opposite would raise suspicion. To avoid that, we recommend for now to have an updated LinkedIn profile. Having one also reduces skepticism, which you would find helpful in the gates of Immigration when they do background checks on you.</p>
<p>However, LinkedIn suffered from data breach in 2012 (<a href="https://blog.linkedin.com/2012/06/06/linkedin-member-passwords-compromised">here</a> and <a href="https://www.pcworld.com/article/257045/6-5m-linkedin-passwords-posted-online-after-apparent-hack.html">here</a>) and in 2016 (<a href="https://blog.linkedin.com/2016/05/18/protecting-our-members">here</a>, <a href="https://www.vice.com/en_us/article/78kk4z/another-day-another-hack-117-million-linkedin-emails-and-password">here</a>, and <a href="https://fortune.com/2016/05/18/linkedin-data-breach-email-password/">here</a>). Although there hasn&rsquo;t been any more reported breaches as of writing this, we can&rsquo;t bet on it yet.</p>
<p>If you have access to more resources, you can make a simple website of your own, and put your CV there, bypassing altogether the need for creating a LinkedIn profile. Plus, you have complete control on what data you&rsquo;d like to share.</p>
<h3 id="reddit">Reddit</h3>

    <figure class="center" >
        <img src="/images/reddit.jpeg"  alt="A screengrab from Red Reader, a Reddit client in F-Droid"   style="border-radius: 8px; max-width:100%;height:auto;"  />

        
            <figcaption class="center"  style="color: 297298;" >As you can see, you can subscribe to as many a diverse topic.</figcaption>
        
    </figure>


<p>Many would argue that Reddit is a forum site, not a social networking site, but that debate is beyond the scope of this post. Still, we include it here, because unlike FB, it centers on anonymity. It also features a voting system (upvote and downvote) that allows the community to judge for themselves what the quality of a post is. In theory, the combination of the two, anonymity and voting system, encourages healthy discussions within forums (subreddits, they are called, or subs). In practice, however, it&rsquo;s more nuanced than that (read: it builds echo chambers). Some subs can be more prone to circlejerking than others.</p>
<p>We recommend to steer clear from the main subreddits as they are, usually, repositories of rubbish content. We also leave it up to you to discern for yourself which ones do foster healthy discussions. Certainly not <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/dankmemes">r/dankmemes</a>, though. You have been advised.</p>
<h3 id="any-rss-feed">Any RSS Feed</h3>

    <figure class="center" >
        <img src="/images/rss.jpeg"  alt="A screengrab showing a feed from an RSS reader"   style="border-radius: 8px; max-width:100%;height:auto;"  />

        
            <figcaption class="center"  style="color: 297298;" >A sample RSS Reader look and feel.</figcaption>
        
    </figure>


<p>According to <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/RSS">Wikipedia</a>:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>RSS (originally RDF Site Summary; later, two competing approaches emerged, which used the backronyms Rich Site Summary and Really Simple Syndication respectively) is a web feed which allows users and applications to access updates to websites in a standardized, computer-readable format.
[&hellip;]
Subscribing to a website RSS removes the need for the user to manually check the website for new content. Instead, their browser constantly monitors the site and informs the user of any updates.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>It&rsquo;s quite similar to Facebook&rsquo;s News Feed, but without the algorithm that pre-selects posts to present to you. With the algorithm, other posts are often drowned out, and sometimes forgotten. It&rsquo;s not so with RSS Feed.</p>
<p>In many RSS Feeds, updates from subscriptions are shown in chronological order by default, entrusting the user the task to select which posts are worth consuming.</p>
<p>When considering what RSS reader to choose, pick the one that&rsquo;s accessible to all platforms (web based, Android, iOS) so you can read Content wherever you want. You may want to start <a href="https://www.slant.co/topics/446/~best-news-readers">here</a>.</p>
<p>Don&rsquo;t know which sites to subscribe to yet? Check this <a href="https://feeder.co/knowledge-base/rss-content/popular-rss-feeds/">list</a> out.</p>
<h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2>
<p>With all the pros and cons enumerated, the answer to the question, &ldquo;Is it worth spending time in FB, or just ditch it altogether?&rdquo; should be &ldquo;Ditch it!&rdquo;</p>
<p>There are many avenues for maintaining connection with other people, and we enlisted some of them here. You should also do your own research when choosing what platform to use, and encourage your family and friends to try and switch with you.
<code>-o)-</code></p>
]]></content>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>That Week We Stayed at Bohol</title>
            <link>/posts/bohol/</link>
            <pubDate>Fri, 29 Nov 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            
            <guid>/posts/bohol/</guid>
            <description>First Day, 22 Nov A short intro to a long travel to airport The day started with the perennial traffic. If you&amp;rsquo;re from Metro Manila, of course, a day of commute starts there. It&amp;rsquo;s not that we didn&amp;rsquo;t almost make it on time to the airport, it&amp;rsquo;s just that we weren&amp;rsquo;t expecting a bad traffic jam on a non-rush hour, but hey, why are we even surprised?
We did make it, though, on time - enough time, even, to have a quick lunch comprising unpalatable highway robbery airport food.</description>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2 id="first-day-22-nov">First Day, 22 Nov</h2>
<h3 id="a-short-intro-to-a-long-travel-to-airport">A short intro to a long travel to airport</h3>
<p>The day started with the perennial traffic. If you&rsquo;re from Metro Manila, of course, a day of commute starts there. It&rsquo;s not that we didn&rsquo;t almost make it on time to the airport, it&rsquo;s just that we weren&rsquo;t expecting a bad traffic jam on a non-rush hour, but hey, why are we even surprised?</p>
<p>We did make it, though, on time - enough time, even, to have a quick lunch comprising unpalatable highway robbery airport food. The traffic situation that plagues the road of Metro Manila has converted the disciplined to disenfranchised in less time - much less time - it takes you to get from Ayala Blvd to&hellip; well, Paseo de Roxas.</p>
<h3 id="arrival-at-bohol">Arrival at Bohol</h3>
<p>When we landed to Panglao Airport, we hopped on an airport service vehicle. Prices are steep, as expected from any airport services, so manage your expectations accordingly. It was about a 40-minute uneventful ride towards our lodging in Tagbilaran, save for the occasional comments of the passengers (the three of us, Isya, Merci [her mother], and Ohio <em>duh</em> on the many an old wooden houses. This was just a small sample of Boholano architecture, and we all like it, simple and old that they are.</p>
<p>Our night stroll let us expose ourselves to the native streets of Tagbilaran, which at some point was filled a plume of smoke from a burning garbage heap inside some gated compound. As &lsquo;Nay Merci noted, &ldquo;Here&rsquo;s no different than Dumaguete [where I&rsquo;m from].&rdquo;</p>
<p>The random zigzagging of our walk landed us on an improptu concert-watching in no less than the San Jose Parish. &ldquo;Adventus&rdquo; it was called, performed by Koro Seraphim, the National Qualifier to the National Music Competitions for Young Artists Foundation (NAMCYA) 2019 Alab ng Musika Competitions, Senior Choir Category.</p>

    <figure class="center" >
        <img src="/images/bohol21.jpeg"  alt="Dome of church"   style="border-radius: 8px; max-width:100%;height:auto;"  />

        
            <figcaption class="center"  style="color: 297298;" >Inside the Parish</figcaption>
        
    </figure>


<h2 id="second-day-23-nov">Second Day, 23 Nov</h2>
<p>We performed the basic functions of tourists in our own country, to explore Bohol&rsquo;s country side. The hotel we were in had offered a travel package the day before, and after considering that the price seemed reasonable, we now have our own driver and sedan to do this touristy trip.</p>
<h3 id="our-first-stop-was-the-baclayon-church">Our first stop was the Baclayon Church.</h3>
<p>Nothing out of the ordinary, really, except that they have their own museum , whose memorabilia, as in all other museums, must not be touched. One of us (not Isya), uncultured that this person in is when it comes to behaving properly, didn&rsquo;t know this fact until he already touched one old wooden artifact <em>before</em> the sign &ldquo;Do not touch anything&rdquo; appeared, replete with a short explainer why (something about the oil in our hands that would later appear and damage the object).</p>

    <figure class="center" >
        <img src="/images/bohol01.jpeg"  alt="A young couple in front of Baclayon Church"   style="border-radius: 8px; max-width:100%;height:auto;"  />

        
            <figcaption class="center"  style="color: 297298;" >First Stop</figcaption>
        
    </figure>



    <figure class="center" >
        <img src="/images/bohol02.jpeg"  alt="A young couple in front of Baclayon Church"   style="border-radius: 8px; max-width:100%;height:auto;"  />

        
            <figcaption class="center"  style="color: 297298;" > </figcaption>
        
    </figure>



    <figure class="center" >
        <img src="/images/bohol20.jpeg"  alt="Side of the Baclayon Church; a dog strolling nearby"   style="border-radius: 8px; max-width:100%;height:auto;"  />

        
            <figcaption class="center"  style="color: 297298;" > </figcaption>
        
    </figure>



    <figure class="center" >
        <img src="/images/bohol18.jpeg"  alt="Detail of an old door of the church"   style="border-radius: 8px; max-width:100%;height:auto;"  />

        
            <figcaption class="center"  style="color: 297298;" >Detail of a wooden door that&#39;s okay for human touch, we think</figcaption>
        
    </figure>



    <figure class="center" >
        <img src="/images/bohol19.jpeg"  alt="two left feet of two different people"   style="border-radius: 8px; max-width:100%;height:auto;"  />

        
            <figcaption class="center"  style="color: 297298;" >Geometric design of floor tiles</figcaption>
        
    </figure>


<h3 id="the-butterfly-garden">The Butterfly Garden</h3>
<p>&hellip;disappointed us, in that it&rsquo;s a claustrophobic experience with the butterflies. At the entrance, visitors are asked to pick the Butterfly Garden and/or Python Area. Only the former had interested us. They claim that some of the butterflies there are exotic species. If so, we asked ourselves, why are they still keeping them for public display?</p>

    <figure class="center" >
        <img src="/images/bohol17.jpeg"  alt="young couple with a banner that says &#39;Welcome to Butterfly Garden&#39; behind them"   style="border-radius: 8px; max-width:100%;height:auto;"  />

        
            <figcaption class="center"  style="color: 297298;" >Look at how &#39;disappointed&#39; we are</figcaption>
        
    </figure>



    <figure class="center" >
        <img src="/images/bohol05.jpeg"  alt="a butterfly"   style="border-radius: 8px; max-width:100%;height:auto;"  />

        
            <figcaption class="center"  style="color: 297298;" >The only one cooperative enough for photo-op</figcaption>
        
    </figure>


<h3 id="lunch-at-loboc-river">Lunch at Loboc River</h3>
<p>More accurately, it&rsquo;s an all-you-can eat buffet on a boat as it cruises to and from the river, while musicians you share the ride with serenade everyone. Be prepared, though: the music is loud. People seem to equate fun with high decibels. They no longer like peace and quiet that Nature brings. It&rsquo;s here that we also note that every component of this touristy affair has been designed efficiently to serve the maximum number of people at the shortest amount of time. Productivity underscores profitability, and thus, in chasing efficiency, tourism (at least in this part of the country) has become mechanical, heartless dare we say. Wait, pardon the digression; such was the effect of food coma.</p>

    <figure class="center" >
        <img src="/images/bohol15.jpeg"  alt="Loboc River"   style="border-radius: 8px; max-width:100%;height:auto;"  />

        
            <figcaption class="center"  style="color: 297298;" >Loboc River</figcaption>
        
    </figure>



    <figure class="center" >
        <img src="/images/bohol06.jpeg"  alt="Loboc River"   style="border-radius: 8px; max-width:100%;height:auto;"  />

        
            <figcaption class="center"  style="color: 297298;" >Loboc River, another view</figcaption>
        
    </figure>



    <figure class="center" >
        <img src="/images/bohol16.jpeg"  alt="A young woman, with Loboc River as her background"   style="border-radius: 8px; max-width:100%;height:auto;"  />

        
            <figcaption class="center"  style="color: 297298;" >&#39;That Lunch, tho!&#39;</figcaption>
        
    </figure>


<h3 id="bilar-loboc-forest">Bilar-Loboc &ldquo;Forest&rdquo;</h3>
<p>Speaking of heartlessness, birds may have developed through millenia of evolution how to spot a not-landing site. That&rsquo;s why in the famed man-made forest, mostly mahogany (a non-native tree), no fowl flock nor frequent. Also, isn&rsquo;t the term &ldquo;man-made forest&rdquo; a bit oxymoronic, if not outright arrogant? All that rant, and still we took pictures just to, uh, prove our point.</p>

    <figure class="center" >
        <img src="/images/bohol03.jpeg"  alt="a young couple in the middle of the road that passes through a forest"   style="border-radius: 8px; max-width:100%;height:auto;"  />

        
            <figcaption class="center"  style="color: 297298;" >How we expressed our disappointment for the man-made forest</figcaption>
        
    </figure>



    <figure class="center" >
        <img src="/images/bohol13.jpeg"  alt="a young woman in a forest"   style="border-radius: 8px; max-width:100%;height:auto;"  />

        
            <figcaption class="center"  style="color: 297298;" >The end of suffering?</figcaption>
        
    </figure>


<h3 id="tarsier-conservation-area">Tarsier Conservation Area</h3>
<p>We also saw Tarsiers, small primates that have got to be nocturnal, or else ultraviolet rays would blind their big eyes. Each one that we saw either slept or kept still under the shades in which they were carefully placed for public viewing. For some who are hoping to see one &ldquo;in the wild&rdquo;, this experience would baffle you, as it did us. The walk inside the conservatory has been limited to a brief mingling with in-house guides as they pointed to the tiny nappers; and it&rsquo;s done on purpose, for better and for worse. To some extent, we understand that tarsiers ultimately do not exist for the pleasure of human entertainment. We do hope that in the future, through the conservatory&rsquo;s efforts, the primates&rsquo; population no longer is endangered.</p>

    <figure class="center" >
        <img src="/images/bohol04.jpeg"  alt="a young couple with a huge sign behind them saying &#39;I love Bohol&#39;"   style="border-radius: 8px; max-width:100%;height:auto;"  />

        
            <figcaption class="center"  style="color: 297298;" >Entrance to the Conservatory</figcaption>
        
    </figure>



    <figure class="center" >
        <img src="/images/bohol14.jpeg"  alt="a foliage"   style="border-radius: 8px; max-width:100%;height:auto;"  />

        
            <figcaption class="center"  style="color: 297298;" >Find the Tarsier</figcaption>
        
    </figure>


<h4 id="interstitial">Interstitial</h4>
<p>We bought a <em>walis-tambo</em> near the Sipatan River in the Municipality of Sevilla. Its handle is made of bamboo, while the actual broom is made of coconut husks, although we sheepishly thought that the fiber closely resembles that of frizzy human hair. We skipped the Hanging Bridges altogether. No, we&rsquo;re not specifically contemptuous against altitudes but to other tourists who were more than willing to take up the space and time of such narrow bridges.</p>

    <figure class="center" >
        <img src="/images/bohol24.jpeg"  alt="the walis-tambo"   style="border-radius: 8px; max-width:100%;height:auto;"  />

        
            <figcaption class="center"  style="color: 297298;" > </figcaption>
        
    </figure>



    <figure class="center" >
        <img src="/images/bohol25.jpeg"  alt="the walis-tambo"   style="border-radius: 8px; max-width:100%;height:auto;"  />

        
            <figcaption class="center"  style="color: 297298;" > </figcaption>
        
    </figure>


<p>Here&rsquo;s the full review of the aforementioned walis (for content, of course):</p>
<ul>
<li>Design: 3/5</li>
<li>Durability: 4/5</li>
<li>Functionality: 2/5</li>
<li>UX: 2/5</li>
</ul>
<p>Overall score: 2.75 out of 5. If you ever see this on your next Bohol trip, we don&rsquo;t recommend you to buy it.</p>
<h3 id="now-the-chocolate-hills">Now, the Chocolate Hills</h3>
<p>are a sight to behold, as cliche as that is. More than a thousand of them - the hills, not tourists - compete for attention, and rightfully so. They each have their own trait: stout, lonely, distant, huge, etc. We only got up on one big hill, developed for the specific purpose of it being the viewing deck on which to view all the other hills surrounding it.</p>

    <figure class="center" >
        <img src="/images/bohol10.jpeg"  alt="a trail of tourists ascending a hill"   style="border-radius: 8px; max-width:100%;height:auto;"  />

        
            <figcaption class="center"  style="color: 297298;" >View from down below...</figcaption>
        
    </figure>



    <figure class="center" >
        <img src="/images/bohol11.jpeg"  alt="viewing deck on a hill"   style="border-radius: 8px; max-width:100%;height:auto;"  />

        
            <figcaption class="center"  style="color: 297298;" >...and up above</figcaption>
        
    </figure>



    <figure class="center" >
        <img src="/images/bohol09.jpeg"  alt=" "   style="border-radius: 8px; max-width:100%;height:auto;"  />

        
            <figcaption class="center"  style="color: 297298;" >An explainer on how the hills were formed</figcaption>
        
    </figure>



    <figure class="center" >
        <img src="/images/bohol12.jpeg"  alt="a young woman smiling, Chocolate Hills is her background"   style="border-radius: 8px; max-width:100%;height:auto;"  />

        
            <figcaption class="center"  style="color: 297298;" >Isya</figcaption>
        
    </figure>



    <figure class="center" >
        <img src="/images/bohol07.jpeg"  alt="a young man smiling, Chocolate Hills is his background"   style="border-radius: 8px; max-width:100%;height:auto;"  />

        
            <figcaption class="center"  style="color: 297298;" >Ohio</figcaption>
        
    </figure>


<h3 id="tuna-republic">Tuna Republic</h3>
<p>Isya has so many memories of this chain of restaurant. This was where they had frequently eaten back on her field days at Agusan del Sur. We had a feast by ordering kinilaw na tuna, sashimi tuna, tinola tuna, grilled tuna belly, rice, and camote. With all the tuna we had, we were worried with the level mercury we have might consumed.</p>
<h2 id="third-day-24-nov">Third Day, 24 Nov</h2>
<p>Free day to do whatever. This thing happens when people travel without a plan. It&rsquo;s not bad per se. In fact, we are freed from the rigidity that plans make us comply, and we liked that. We had our breakfast near seaport. Our late lunch at Bee Farm Cafe in Island City Mall was the highlight of the day. In a simple day, food has to be the highlight in an otherwise relaxed pace.</p>
<h2 id="fourth-day-25-nov">Fourth Day, 25 Nov</h2>
<p>For an island surrounded by seas, potable water in Bohol is hard to come by. Every drink must be bought or paid for. If it&rsquo;s free, doubt yourself first before having the guts (literally) to drink it. Each cup of water must be sought after amid the choking thirst.</p>
<p>Swimming in the beach helped. When we transferred from Tagbilaran to Panglao that afternoon, it&rsquo;s the only thing to look forward to: the almost-white sand shoreline littered with foreign bodies and boats with the setting sun as backdrop.</p>

    <figure class="center" >
        <img src="/images/bohol08.jpeg"  alt="a small cliff side by the beach"   style="border-radius: 8px; max-width:100%;height:auto;"  />

        
            <figcaption class="center"  style="color: 297298;" >Sunset at the Alona Beach</figcaption>
        
    </figure>


<p>In the night, a different life emerged from slumber. Commercialization as an economic tool for tourism had changed this quiet beach into something noisy, smelly, and shiny, as if an introvert remodeling their habits to conform with peer pressure.</p>
<h2 id="fifth-day-26-nov">Fifth Day, 26 Nov</h2>
<p>Ohio flew back to Manila. &ldquo;With what I saw, I&rsquo;m not fond of Bohol&rdquo; would be the personal feedback to give to those asking for anecdotes, but these experiences take time to process. (If it&rsquo;s sounding too BS now, it&rsquo;s probably because of the unpleasant experience of having to deal with airport security over a foldable bread knife. Not cool!)</p>
<p>Sorry to hear about Ohio&rsquo;s experience with the new Panglao Airport having to confiscate his stainless foldable bread knife without even bothering to confiscate his wooden chopsticks (both, by the way, can be deadly weapons) which were a part of the mess kit.</p>
<p>We, Isya and Merci, stayed behind for one more night to supposedly have more beach time. Strapped for cash, they were unable to watch the dolphins and do island hopping.</p>
<p>So, we decided to have lunch on the famous Bohol Bee Farm restaurant which seems to be a resort also. It was Isya&rsquo;s first time to visit the place but Merci had been there numerous times, and she was shocked with all the development and expansion.</p>
<p>Isya did not find the expensive things there impressive at all. Recall the meal we (Isya and Ohio) had at the Bohol Bee Farm cafe in Island City Mall - it was cheaper. One positive thing about the lunch is enjoying the pineapple and basil juice. It&rsquo;s one of those marriages of ingredients that make a pricey drink worth it.</p>
<p>Even with all the restaurants and bars in Alona beach, it seems to be missing Japanese restaurants. We, Isya and Merci, combed the the stretch of the beach looking for one because Merci was craving for some Japanese dishes, and we found none. We settled with Lost Horizon restaurant, a beachfront dining with a live band playing songs of the oldies.</p>
<h2 id="sixth-day-27-nov">Sixth Day, 27 Nov</h2>
<p>On the last day of our trip, we looked back (almost literally) on why we appreciate the second inn that we booked, called <!-- raw HTML omitted -->Walkerz Travellers Inn<!-- raw HTML omitted -->. Its distance from the Alona Beach not only provided serenity during our stay, it also required exercise to get to the main road, although the 7-minute walk is never that pleasant so long as the ways are still muddy, rocky, and unpaved.</p>
<p>We made sure to check the Panglao Public Market in for local weaved baskets. We didn&rsquo;t bring home any, though.</p>
<p>Next stop: St. Augustine Church which was about 400 meters away from the market. Beside the church is a Catholic school, and not far from it is the barangay hall. Isya wasn&rsquo;t keen on stepping inside the church while the floor was being mopped. After Merci took pictures of the inside, they decided to look at the park nearby.</p>
<p>On our way out, Merci saw two men holding sticks with large nets which she recognized as contraption for catching stray dogs. Merci, always inquisitive, asked them what they were doing. They said they were from the provincial veterinary office, and were out to catch dogs. After the exchange, we learned that the dogs they caught would be brought back to the barangay hall, to be confined in their backyard. If, after three days, no one claimed them they would be euthanized. However, euthanasia is simply our place-holder here, as we haven&rsquo;t really verified how they put down the dogs.</p>
<p>They allowed us see the dogs they caught. What we saw was heartbreaking - rows of cages were lined up at the back of the barangay hall by the mangroves without roofing. They were exposed to elements. The first cage housed a very sick dog who was having a hard time sitting and laying down because of an inflamed wound at the rear part of its body. The dog wailed in pain, and hearing it only worsened whatever sickness we&rsquo;re already feeling.</p>
<p>We tried to find out more by asking a man there, but he seemed to be just passing by. Merci couldn&rsquo;t help but break down when we were finally out in the open area. She wondered how the church, just a few steps away, wouldn&rsquo;t do anything about the plight of the stray dogs being impounded. There was no compassion.</p>
<p>Most of the street dogs became stray as a result human irresponsibility. There are humane ways to handle this issue of high numbers stray dogs. One of the most effective so far is Trap-Neuter-Vaccine-Release (TNVR) program which local government units can implement. The concerned community can also participate through sponsorships and volunteerism.</p>
<p>There was a defeated feeling after this encounter, a kind of helplessness of not being able to do anything immediately. We walked towards the public market to wait for the bus shuttle. By this time, we needed to go back at the inn to prepare for our flight that afternoon.</p>
<h2 id="parting-thoughts-by-isya">Parting thoughts, by Isya</h2>
<p>The Bohol trip was a break from the pressures of city life. It&rsquo;s also a chance to be with the people I love, and to spend time with them. But the Bohol I had longed for, the one my mother, Merci, had talked about years ago, was nowhere near the descriptions of peace and quiet in those stories. It could be that I have just high expectations of it not being another touristy crowded place. <code>-o)-</code></p>
]]></content>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>Plants as Trash Deterrent?</title>
            <link>/posts/plants-deterrent/</link>
            <pubDate>Tue, 15 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            
            <guid>/posts/plants-deterrent/</guid>
            <description>A staple in both landscaping and urban planning is adding a natural element in an otherwise human-made environment. Depending on the budget, it could be a fountain to provide a water element; or it could be as simple as adding plants along sidewalks. In places all over, we have seen good and bad implementations of these natural elements, but the most common perhaps is the latter â€” plants.
Exhibit A People have concluded that this plant box (and many others) is where to place their trash.</description>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A staple in both landscaping and urban planning is adding a natural element in an otherwise human-made environment. Depending on the budget, it could be a fountain to provide a water element; or it could be as simple as adding plants along sidewalks. In places all over, we have seen good and bad implementations of these natural elements, but the most common perhaps is the latter â€” plants.</p>
<h2 id="exhibit-a">Exhibit A</h2>
<p>People have concluded that this plant box (and many others) is where to place their trash. A dead shrub remains standing, with the help of another dead wood, in spite of its fate. Whether garbage caused it to die, we cannot verify. But surely, single-use plastics have better places to go, and better forms to be, i.e. in their original state as fossil fuel deep beneath the earth, untouched and unprocessed by human greed.</p>

    <figure class="center" >
        <img src="/images/pb01.jpeg"  alt="A plant box on a sidewalk, littered with garbage"   style="border-radius: 8px; max-width:100%;height:auto;"  />

        
            <figcaption class="center"  style="color: 297298;" >Since when did we begin to mistake these for garbage bins?</figcaption>
        
    </figure>


<h2 id="exhibit-b">Exhibit B</h2>
<p>On a different location, owners of a nearby hardware store populated a similar plant box with many potted plants on the base of the trunk. It is aided by a sign, as if the greens themselves warn passers-by. In English, &ldquo;No Trash Here. Fine of Php 2000, or Jail Time. -Ordinance by City Hall&rdquo; The ordinance part seems sketchy, but who are we to speculate over such matter?</p>

    <figure class="center" >
        <img src="/images/pb02.jpeg"  alt="A plantbox on a sidewalk, with small potted plants covering its base"   style="border-radius: 8px; max-width:100%;height:auto;"  />

        
            <figcaption class="center"  style="color: 297298;" >Plants discourage pedestrians from littering in the box; it&#39;s never the warning sign.</figcaption>
        
    </figure>


<p>Can we then conclude that plants can be used as natural deterrent against environment trashers?</p>
<p>However, several days after taking the pictures above, plant boxes on exhibit A and B are sadly no more. No thanks to the local government unit&rsquo;s clearing operations, neither plants nor their boxes survived. We wouldn&rsquo;t have really known if they&rsquo;re trash deterrent. <code>-o)-</code></p>

    <figure class="center" >
        <img src="/images/pb03.jpeg"  alt="Concrete and soil debris where a plant box used to be"   style="border-radius: 8px; max-width:100%;height:auto;"  />

        
            <figcaption class="center"  style="color: 297298;" >Clearing operations in favor of pedestrians?</figcaption>
        
    </figure>


]]></content>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>Many days meshing into a manifesto (of sorts)</title>
            <link>/posts/manifesto/</link>
            <pubDate>Mon, 19 Aug 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            
            <guid>/posts/manifesto/</guid>
            <description>THE FACTUAL PIECES here shall be made obvious when necessary, so try to make allowances for every entry. They say that when two opposite states of matter coexist at a single point in time, it&amp;rsquo;s believed to be in superposition unless an observer finds themself literate enough of the ways to approach such nuance. Accordingly, these statements are neither true nor false until someone (you, the observer?) comes along, and formulates a theory that we can together test.</description>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>THE FACTUAL PIECES here shall be made obvious when necessary, so try to make allowances for every entry. They say that when two opposite states of matter coexist at a single point in time, it&rsquo;s believed to be in superposition unless an observer finds themself literate enough of the ways to approach such nuance. Accordingly, these statements are neither true nor false until someone (you, <em>the</em> observer?) comes along, and formulates a theory that we can together test.</p>
<p>In getting involved, something to think about: How does one allocate the limited resources of oneâ€™s being in search for truth? Not all truths can be discovered because we are finite. And in many cases, it is subjective.</p>
<hr>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<h2 id="horoscopenow">Horoscope&hellip;now!</h2>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p><strong>Aries</strong>: This is the second best time to quit your addiction to senseless rumination. The best time to quit will be later, when you have thought it through.
Lucky number: 11101 |
Lucky color: #717171</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p><strong>Taurus</strong>: Rain shall fall upon thy parched garden. When tending to it, try not to use a raincoat. let the water seep in.
Lucky number: 1000101 |
Lucky color: #FFCFCD</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p><strong>Gemini</strong>: focus only on the top 6 priorities on your to-do list, if you have one. if you don&rsquo;t have one, go make a list on what you should be doing in this part of your life, and do the first 6. If the newly-made list comprises only of less than 6 items, congratulations! You&rsquo;re actually an Aries in Gemini&rsquo;s clothes.
Lucky number: 10000 |
Lucky color: #E1AD01</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<hr>
<p>DO YOU REMEMBER your first few seconds, first few hours on your first job? A secret knot tightens itself in the stomach. You think this is exciting, to put forth something that you came up with, in exchange of money. What you may not have known then is that framing matters. Depending on what life one lead prior to their first (legal) employment, a job could provide a structure in one&rsquo;s life. Or it could disrupt a routine.</p>
<p>And then, the world continues to evolve, and they will continue to monitor your progress. People go up and down the ladder. Some of them run faster than you do, but you tell yourself that you will maintain a pace that will sustain a constant energy level. &ldquo;It&rsquo;s about pacing,&rdquo; you mumble, looking at younger colleagues climbing faster than you.</p>
<p>Few years later, you find yourself in multiple places, jumping from job to job, hoping to find a fit somewhere along the jaunt. A vermin in search of a vehicle in which to play songs, reanimating long-ago feelings, reviving a deadening pursuit. Each commute becomes a process of self-discovery, because you choose to learn about yourself in the hours you are stuck in the daily grid lock. Perhaps, the purpose pushes off the dream back to the pits, but the area where it decays is itself shrinking. What, then?</p>
<p>Greed unknowingly becomes the motif that pushes from beneath, but it is tiring to accommodate it. So greed becomes greenwashed into a different brand. But that brand feels sketched by wobbly hands, details misplaced in spots, and because it is.</p>
<hr>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p><strong>Cancer</strong>: Unless you have a formal education on psychiatry, stop giving people advice from pop articles you read from the Internet. If you do have a formal education on psychiatry, would you kindly drop us a note? We&rsquo;d like to check ourselves for mental glitches.
Lucky number: 10 |
Lucky color: #002D5E</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p><strong>Leo</strong>: It would be more productive if you could start learning on how you can grow your own food garden. But it&rsquo;s fine if you can&rsquo;t; we all need take some time to learn something outside our expertise.
lucky number: 10101 |
lucky color: #7FFFD4</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p><strong>Virgo</strong>: The photos you have been posting on social media sites should remain minimal AND un-filtered. They represent the flaws of humanity; keep it real.
lucky number: 1010 |
lucky color: #E20085</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<hr>
<p>EXAMINED MYSELF ON a normal day. I checked out how I looked that day on its opaque surface. Nothing gazed back at me, no surprise in that. I could not have possibly forgotten the only accredited (inter)face I have, but the idea has intrigued me just now. If I, the user of this body, only had the time to be patient with how each of me works, craves, despises, there would be no time for me to be overwhelmed when something bad triggers. I&rsquo;d be prepared to fill in the hollow steps in this bolero. For now, though, there&rsquo;s no beginning for the user&rsquo;s patience, a small problem I&rsquo;m willing to forego.</p>
<hr>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p><strong>Libra</strong>: Information, and of course, knowledge should be available to everyone at little to no cost. Your mission today is to give your favorite book to someone you think most needs it. Tell them to do the same once they&rsquo;re finished reading it.
Lucky number: 10111 |
Lucky color: #27111A</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p><strong>Scorpio</strong>: Instead of nicotine, try cannabis. If that&rsquo;s hard to come by, try Fentanyl. Or a glass of water. You should definitely just drink water.
Lucky number: 11 |
Lucky color: #8D9E5D</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p><strong>Sagittarius</strong>: When funding your travels, design it in such a way that you&rsquo;ll leave the least amount of carbon footprint. E.g.: Why don&rsquo;t you explore first your local neighborhood before venturing out to Antarctica?
Lucky number: 1100000 |
Lucky color: #FCFFFE</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<hr>
<p>WE TEND TO hold on to a fluid file that gradually, perpetually slips away from our grasp, our memory. The humbling fact that our physiology is borne out of limitations, will sponsor many an angry idea, yet I&rsquo;ll still go by my courtesy that our minds can only do so much.</p>
<p>It was a clear picture at first. But since it reacts &ndash; fades &ndash; with time, the picture becomes just a sheet, splotches indicating inaccuracy, the metadata no longer readable. The sheet resembles the existence of a feeling, but what feeling, it&rsquo;s difficult to recall.</p>
<p>(What the picture depicts: a small atrium inside a police station that functioned as a waiting area where cops lounged. Two vending machines hummed, one of them already had its lights flickering. It could all be a practical joke, you thought, as you thumped with pelvis the one with still its lights on. A burning corpse by the floor filled the air with light smoke, choking you when you shouldn&rsquo;t even be alive. Nothing is wrong, you said.)</p>
<p>It&rsquo;s weird, <em>no</em>, considering that we being emotional, social creatures, to have misplaced somewhere along the spacetime what we have felt for a particular instance. When then, do we stop rewriting a figment?</p>
<hr>
<hr>
<p>JUST A MINUTE past noon &ndash; come to think of it, there are plenty of pleasant smells polluting the boring air.</p>
<p>My favorite, for the longest time now, dates back to my high school days, when I used to frequent a good friend&rsquo;s house. The scent, I found out much, much later, is associated with that of a wild orchid&rsquo;s. That info is according to a liquid hand soap that triggered this smell memory. Whether this is accurate, I&rsquo;m not sure; I&rsquo;d like to find out by smelling one out there in the wild.</p>
<p>What is your favorite smell?</p>
<hr>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p><strong>Capricorn</strong>: Stay away from night markets. Before you sleep, realize the amount of garbage they sell and produce in each stall.
Lucky number: 110010 |
Lucky color: #00E699</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p><strong>Aquarius</strong>: You will be designing a better product for PWDs, because they are in it, too.
Lucky number: 101001 |
Lucky color: #080808</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p><strong>Pisces</strong>: Before deciding what school you&rsquo;ll take your undergraduate or post-graduate studies in, know this: Universities are driven by business-minded preachers. Bless you, then, if you decide to go to a state diploma mill.
Lucky number: 10001 |
Lucky color: #820000</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<hr>
<p>WHILE NOT ENTIRELY birthed from the need to catalogue every journey, this gravity between two bodies orbiting one another came to be as an agreement to force them to list as many of their thoughts  as they can, as accurate and precise as they can, sans scientific scripture backing each thesis. This might mean an epistolary bible they can look back to when, for example, dinner talks with relatives produces nothing but the droning of proverbial provincial crickets. This may or may not be the crossroads of our personal endeavors, but we are certain to inject some of our advocacy whenever we can. Whatever wall of text you chance upon here, we hope that you take the time to digest it before deciding what to do with the pulp. <code>-o)-</code></p>
]]></content>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>Taiwan Trip, June 2019, (Part 2 of 2)</title>
            <link>/posts/taiwan-part2/</link>
            <pubDate>Sun, 28 Jul 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            
            <guid>/posts/taiwan-part2/</guid>
            <description>Have you read Part 1?
Day 3 We ate breakfast in McDo, the one near the place we stayed in, and it didnâ€™t serve any local variant of Taiwan&amp;rsquo;s food. It&amp;rsquo;s all hamburgers, fried chicken, and sausage McNothinâ€™. Some would say that eating at a known (read: exploitive capitalist) fast food chain, one that you also have in your country, is a disservice to the self to get to know the locals or their food, but that wasnâ€™t our case.</description>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>Have you read <a href="/posts/taiwan-part1/">Part 1</a></em>?</p>
<h2 id="day-3">Day 3</h2>
<p>We ate breakfast in McDo, the one near the place we stayed in, and it didnâ€™t serve any local variant of Taiwan&rsquo;s food. It&rsquo;s all hamburgers, fried chicken, and sausage McNothinâ€™. Some would say that eating at a known (read: exploitive capitalist) fast food chain, one that you also have in your country, is a disservice to the self to get to know the locals or their food, but that wasnâ€™t our case. This particular breakfast had us mingling with the locals. Saturday morning &ndash; wolfing on a large breakfast meal; seeing kids being tutored at the other table; old couple eating their favorite grease-rich food after a walk; a father sharing a hearty meal with his son before a soccer game &ndash; it was at a Mcdonaldâ€™s joint where we had the most telling glimpse of the locals in their element, and somehow, we belonged.</p>

    <figure class="center" >
        <img src="/images/twMC01.jpg"  alt="A view of Mcdonald&#39;s from the MRT station"   style="border-radius: 8px; max-width:100%;height:auto;"  />

        
            <figcaption class="center"  style="color: 297298;" >Breakfast at Mcdo before the days adventure</figcaption>
        
    </figure>


<p>The guesthouse we had stayed in is just two blocks from the MRT Station of the Brown Line. One of the destinations along this Brown Line are the Taipei Zoo and Maokong Gondola, the latter being the last station. We skipped the zoo because we donâ€™t like looking down on animals in confined spaces. So the gondola it was.</p>
<p>The Maokong Gondola reveals an altitude we have never seen before. The mountain trees (not sure what they are) relax the tired eyes, although there still looms the urban side of Taipei, not far below, sharing the view. The dense forested area below gondolasâ€™ route makes it bearable to think that on the unlikely chance that the cables snap, the trees would cushion our fall. Of course, no such thing happened. We were safe, and made it to Zhinan Temple Station, a Taoist Temple. Signs in golden calligraphy immediately caught our eyes as we entered the compound.</p>
<p>We have an inkling that Taiwanese people liked building temples. â€œWhat for?â€ we wondered. For maintaining their spirituality in spite of their trudge for Future? For tourists? Find the answer in its oriental architecture.</p>
<p>After the â€œspiritualâ€ stint in Temple, we caught another gondola ride to the last station, the Maokong station. Naturally, it is where the tourists gravitate, being a haven for both tea cafes and restaurants. Hiking trails also proliferate the area, perfect for walking buffs.</p>

    <figure class="center" >
        <img src="/images/twMG01.jpg"  alt="Gondola Ride with the view of nature and Taipei 101 at a distance"   style="border-radius: 8px; max-width:100%;height:auto;"  />

        
            <figcaption class="center"  style="color: 297298;" >Breathtaking view from great heights</figcaption>
        
    </figure>



    <figure class="center" >
        <img src="/images/twMG02.jpg"  alt="Ohio and Isya chilling inside the gondola"   style="border-radius: 8px; max-width:100%;height:auto;"  />

        
            <figcaption class="center"  style="color: 297298;" >Chilling and taking a selfie</figcaption>
        
    </figure>



    <figure class="center" >
        <img src="/images/twMG03.jpg"  alt="Clear gondolas offers 360 unobstructed view"   style="border-radius: 8px; max-width:100%;height:auto;"  />

        
            <figcaption class="center"  style="color: 297298;" >Looking down on the canopies</figcaption>
        
    </figure>



    <figure class="center" >
        <img src="/images/twMG05.jpg"  alt="A gondola"   style="border-radius: 8px; max-width:100%;height:auto;"  />

        
            <figcaption class="center"  style="color: 297298;" >Gondola and station</figcaption>
        
    </figure>



    <figure class="center" >
        <img src="/images/twMG06.jpg"  alt="A view of temple"   style="border-radius: 8px; max-width:100%;height:auto;"  />

        
            <figcaption class="center"  style="color: 297298;" >Temple hopping no. 1</figcaption>
        
    </figure>



    <figure class="center" >
        <img src="/images/twMG08.jpg"  alt="A person with her chinese zodiac: Snake"   style="border-radius: 8px; max-width:100%;height:auto;"  />

        
            <figcaption class="center"  style="color: 297298;" >Isya and the stone snake at the entrance of one of the temples</figcaption>
        
    </figure>



    <figure class="center" >
        <img src="/images/twMG12.jpg"  alt="Offering prayers under the red lanterns inside the temple"   style="border-radius: 8px; max-width:100%;height:auto;"  />

        
            <figcaption class="center"  style="color: 297298;" >Temple hopping no.2</figcaption>
        
    </figure>


<p>So many things to do, so many places to see in this part of Maokong. Isya insisted on checking out the kettle holes and tea promotion building where we thought we could see an actual tea plantation. By then, it was way past lunchtime. All the walking we made up and down the winding roads, just to look for the best tea house had made us exhausted. Perhaps it was the combination of hunger and weariness that pushed us to continue searching for kettle holes and the tea promotion area. By the time we got to the latter, we could no longer ignore the grumbling of our stomachs. We headed straight to one of the tea restaurants, supposedly with high ratings, if weâ€™re to believe the Google reviews.</p>
<p>In spite of what weâ€™re already feeling, weâ€™re still game for some adventure. On our way to the selected restaurant, we saw the sign to kettle holes. We debated whether itâ€™s wise to tread down a steep slope, but empty stomachs gave us no wits for this misplaced adventurism, and we finally convinced ourselves to â€œmake the most out of it.â€ Down the stairwell we went to the kettle holes. After hundreds of steps going down, several stream bends, and some towering ferns, one would hope that this better be worth it. Alas, the sight of the overrated kettle holes was anticlimactic. Though, better sight were the paths of ferns leading to other trails.  Also, a hanging bridge, guarded by stone cats and pandas on both ends, sway over the stream. These adorable statues delighted Isya, so much that she began cooing, as she is wont to do at the presence of such benevolence, cute or otherwise, flesh or stone.</p>
<p>On our way back, the flight of stairs became a million steps. <em>Tita</em> Isya had to endure the ascent with cramps forming on her right leg, and a breath sheâ€™s running out of.</p>
<p>We ended in a tea place called Yao Yue Tea House, a highly rated place in Wenshan. The place reminded us of Japanense aesthetics. We sat outside for an overlooking view of the hillside, near another couple who was already there. The oolong tea we ordered was served with a complete tea set, and was meant to be the traditional way. The menu came with a how-to-have-tea, so we made sure to follow them. We had chao fan, dumplings, and sweet and sour fish.</p>

    <figure class="center" >
        <img src="/images/twTT01.jpg"   style="border-radius: 8px; max width:100%;height:auto;"  />

        
    </figure>



    <figure class="center" >
        <img src="/images/twTT02.jpg"   style="border-radius: 8px; max width:100%;height:auto;"  />

        
    </figure>



    <figure class="center" >
        <img src="/images/twTT03.jpg"   style="border-radius: 8px; max width:100%;height:auto;"  />

        
    </figure>



    <figure class="center" >
        <img src="/images/twTT04.jpg"   style="border-radius: 8px; max width:100%;height:auto;"  />

        
    </figure>


<p>After the late lunch, we decided to head out for Taipei 101, to get to know how monumental it really is up close.</p>
<p>Good thing that the street outside the tea house, is also a bus route that we could hop on to take us to the MRT. Waiting with the bus ride with us were two middle-aged people (a couple?). They asked us if a bus would pass by the tea place, to which we replied yes. The couple spoke Mandarin but are not from Taiwan. It was also their first time to visit. If we had to guess, they are either from Singapore, Malaysia or mainland China.</p>
<p>The couple was waiting for a different bus number. Some 20 minutes had passed, a bus began approaching, going down the direction of the mountain. Isya thought that this might be the bus to hop onto, so she flagged it down. When the door swung open, the driver didnâ€™t exactly let us in. There was irritation in the way he spoke, but we didnâ€™t understand any of it. We got the hint that this wasnâ€™t the bus. Ohio felt embarrassed in this short affair.</p>
<p>Another 10 minutes, another bus passed by on the way to Maokong Gondola station. Knowing it was not our bus, we didn&rsquo;t bother to flag it down. But the couple who were with us did. However, the driver didnâ€™t let them in yet, as he had to finish the trip, which only meant going to the end point, the Maokong Gondola station, before returning. Not to worry, though, the couple said when they reported back to us, that that exact bus should be back in no time.</p>
<p>Meanwhile, we all got to talking, not minding the obvious language barrier. People will always find ways to connect with one another, looking for something to share with. In this case, a bus took the shape of the common denominator. When the bus returned, the couple were kind enough to offer to ask the driver if it would pass by any MRT station along its route. â€œAny MRT would do,â€ we told the couple, and from there, we could again navigate Taipei by ourselves.</p>
<p>The driver essentially said yes. We all boarded the bus. Drum rolls halt; curtains fall. Looking back on it, itâ€™s nice to know there are still good-hearted people, some of them are even willing to bridge the babel between strangers.</p>

    <figure class="center" >
        <img src="/images/twT101.jpg"   style="border-radius: 8px; max width:100%;height:auto;"  />

        
    </figure>


<h2 id="day-4">Day 4</h2>
<h3 id="reportage-on-isyas-30th-birthday">Reportage on Isya&rsquo;s 30th birthday:</h3>
<p>The morning was supposed to be celebrated on Yehliu Geopark, but we got out of bed late.</p>
<p>Had we really intended to rise early, what would have we done there?</p>
<p>Meditation, perhaps, by the boulders, attempting to learn the chemistry of earth and sea if only we understood their clashing methods. In order to study rocks, one must be wary of navigating their interface, first by sight, then by hand.</p>
<p>Biking is also one form of getting around the Geopark, we heard. It would have been another form of meditation, too, with the added benefit of aerobics.</p>
<p>But, we got out of bed late, like we said. Time is relative, Einstein notioned, and in the cozy abode in which we lost sleep, time were the hours spent motionless, in rest instead of in preparation. In our daily reflection, we gave up on the idea of traveling for two hours just to see some weird rock formation.</p>
<p>So we settled for a nearby venue: Huashan Creative Park. The Park showcased talents from different artists. Lots of pretty hand-made items we could have bought as souvenirs, if only one of us werenâ€™t so strict with budget.</p>
<p>In one of the buildings in the Park, we ate lunch at Alleycat&rsquo;s, a pizzeria that already offers alcoholic drinks as early as noon. Our bill spiked to NTD 1,056 for the pizza and several little dishes we ordered. Not good, or charge to experience?</p>

    <figure class="center" >
        <img src="/images/twCP03.jpg"   style="border-radius: 8px; max width:100%;height:auto;"  />

        
    </figure>



    <figure class="center" >
        <img src="/images/twCP01.jpg"   style="border-radius: 8px; max width:100%;height:auto;"  />

        
    </figure>



    <figure class="center" >
        <img src="/images/twCP02.jpg"   style="border-radius: 8px; max width:100%;height:auto;"  />

        
    </figure>


<p>Several MRT stations away, we found loitering in the greenery of Daâ€™an Forest Park. Here we increased our steps while taking in the view, watching people what they do in forest parks.</p>
<p>Parks are meant to be inclusive, as Daâ€™an Forest Park is. Plenty of seats are provided for old people when they get tired. Some ambulatory aisles have been fitted with handrails for people on rehabilitation, when they are still regaining the power of their legs. Ramps make it accessible for wheelchairs, trolleys, and other wheeled contraptions.</p>
<p>An orchestra was performing on an open auditorium in Da&rsquo;an Forest Park. The acoustics of the place, surprisingly, makes it easy for visitors to hear all the different notes of all the different instruments playing. We stuck around for awhile, until they finished their rendition of a Michael Jackson mixtape.</p>
<p>Our last stop for the day before retiring to bed was Shilin Night Market. Hereâ€™s a short list of our purchases:</p>
<ul>
<li>Fried dumplings worth NTD 50; tasty and plentiful, a good food intro before diving into the heart of the night market</li>
<li>Grilled octopus tentacle worth NTD 140; expensive for its bland taste, donâ€™t eat.</li>
<li>Stinky tofu worth NTD 80; while okay on its own, it could have been better if we ate it with a small bowl of rice.</li>
<li>Milk tea holder worth NTD 100; a gift to bring back home, but also serves as a template for Isya for her to make thousands more of it.</li>
<li>Sticker worth NTD 30; pink, with the image of two fists bumping headlined by the words &ldquo;real friends&rdquo; all in capital letters.</li>
</ul>

    <figure class="center" >
        <img src="/images/twSH01.jpg"   style="border-radius: 8px; max width:100%;height:auto;"  />

        
    </figure>



    <figure class="center" >
        <img src="/images/twSH02.jpg"   style="border-radius: 8px; max width:100%;height:auto;"  />

        
    </figure>



    <figure class="center" >
        <img src="/images/twSH03.jpg"   style="border-radius: 8px; max width:100%;height:auto;"  />

        
    </figure>



    <figure class="center" >
        <img src="/images/twSH04.jpg"   style="border-radius: 8px; max width:100%;height:auto;"  />

        
    </figure>


<h2 id="day-5">Day 5</h2>
<p>Late lunch at Tamed Fox. <em>Late</em> being the operative word here, and probably a favorite of ours, given our tendency to stay up late and wake up late.</p>
<p>Funny thing: we went to this Tamed Fox restaurant in search of a carrot cake. A craving for carrot cake had stirred Isya for her birthday, but when faced with the fact that thereâ€™s a shortage of it in Taipei, she was all the more determined to look for one. Ohio, on the other hand, looked up for restaurants, pastry shops, and bakeries that serve the best carrot cakes. On our research, we found instead doughnut thatâ€™s supposed to taste like carrot cake, in this artsy/healthy restaurant named Tamed Fox. We were excited to try them.</p>
<p>Alas, when itâ€™s time to order asked for their doughnut, the server told us that it has been a long time since they last sold those doughnuts. You see, it has been removed from their menu. Powerless then Isya became, and her heart, now a million pieces all over, could only be mended by settling for a matcha coconut milk drink.</p>
<p>After realizing we just had an expensive lunch &ndash; the healthy options on the menu could simply be their marketing tool to jack the price up &ndash; we made got our hands wet when we made our own paper at Suho Paper Museum. Itâ€™s a memorial built to honor its founder. Itâ€™s also Suhoâ€™s (the founder, duh) response to Taiwanâ€™s lacking of paper museum at the time.</p>
<p>The roof deck provided a wonderful view of the busy district.</p>

    <figure class="center" >
        <img src="/images/twSP01.jpg"   style="border-radius: 8px; max width:100%;height:auto;"  />

        
    </figure>



    <figure class="center" >
        <img src="/images/twSP02.jpg"   style="border-radius: 8px; max width:100%;height:auto;"  />

        
    </figure>



    <figure class="center" >
        <img src="/images/twSP03.jpg"   style="border-radius: 8px; max width:100%;height:auto;"  />

        
    </figure>


<p>On our way to Eslite Bookshop, we witnessed a car accident, known in Filipino slang as &lsquo;carambola&rsquo;. This particular one involved four vehicles on a single lane bumping into each other because the one on the front may have floored the brake too hard, so that it ensues further miscalculations for the drivers behind him. These kinds of accidents still happen in a city more disciplined than Manila. Isya inferred, &ldquo;As long as there are cars, and there are humans driving them, there will always be car accidents.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Eslite bookshop is a wonderful tourist destination, it is a five story bookstore that operates 24/7. Its presence in the heart of the city just goes to show that Taiwanese hold high regard to reading. The promise of knowledge contained in books is always enticing to come and open its pages, especially if the cover captures my attention. We were told not to judge them by appearance alone, but the books in Eslite Bookshop hold many promises, if only we could read the characters. Definitely, we would like to spend more time if only we were not confined to reading only English alphabet letters. It doesnâ€™t only house books but is also a place to showcase arts and crafts.</p>
<h2 id="day-6">Day 6</h2>
<p>Last day on the busy Taipei. We got up late, went outside by noon to have lunch for the second time on a nearby eatery. Most of the viands are vegetables, all of which I find palatable.</p>
<p>Second only to Fuyang Eco Park, I find Dahu Park, one of my favorite places we went to. The lack of people (at the time, at least) definitely made it more attractive. Plus, the building on the entrance has an indoor swimming pool. Will we ever get to practice our breast strokes there?</p>

    <figure class="center" >
        <img src="/images/twGP01.jpg"   style="border-radius: 8px; max width:100%;height:auto;"  />

        
    </figure>



    <figure class="center" >
        <img src="/images/twGP02.jpg"   style="border-radius: 8px; max width:100%;height:auto;"  />

        
    </figure>


<p>They also built a memorial hall for Sun Yat Sen, another of Taiwan&rsquo;s founding fathers, though not as grand as Chiang Kai-Shek&rsquo;s.</p>
<p>Our last major stop was the Songshan Cultural Park. It was where we ate dinner, and tried my first (and last) cold brew coffee WITH lemonade. I bought my first (and, due to the price, possibly last) Leuchtturm1917 there, with a Bauhaus theme.</p>
<p>We witnessed a scooter catching fire. Two fire trucks were quick to respond to the scene, and in no time, they put out the fire. Not many tourists could go back home and have that story with them.</p>
<h2 id="day-7">Day 7</h2>
<p>Back to Manila, where else?</p>
<p>Hotter is its afternoon than Taipei. Hotter still is its smog, but in its familiarity we reveled instead our memories of the alien land from which we had to leave. Our lives are here, in Manila, for now; and in its strange new buildings, we tried looking for tiled facades.</p>
<h2 id="closing-notes-epilogue">Closing Notes, Epilogue</h2>
<p>Isya has been stressing about bed bug bites she had the whole trip, which might be an allergic reaction. It was super itchy and warm that it woke her up in the middle of the night to scratch the bites. Yes, it was a big not to scratch inflamed bites but the itch was agonizing and torturous. What is more stressing is the fact that we couldnâ€™t figure out where she got the bites because Ohio never got any. So, the source might not be in our bedroom, let alone on the bed. And itâ€™s entirely improbable itâ€™s in something we ate, because we practically ate the same food. The only possible source would be during our hike at the Fuyang Eco park on our very first day at Taipei.</p>
<p>On Day 3, we did get to the Tower. If youâ€™re the type of person who never liked being surrounded by many people, consider this: Taipei 101 might seem overrated, but seeing it in person cannot be, uh, <em>overlooked</em>.</p>
<p>On Day 5, we had <em>another</em> lunch &ndash; ramen &ndash; after our visit in Suho Paper Museum. At the unholy afternoon hour, no one else was in the diner, and we wondered whether we were early for dinner.
Lastly, here are interesting pics of clean Taiwan streets. Go find them. <code>-o)-</code></p>
<p>
    <figure class="center" >
        <img src="/images/twST01.jpg"   style="border-radius: 8px; max width:100%;height:auto;"  />

        
    </figure>



    <figure class="center" >
        <img src="/images/twST02.jpg"   style="border-radius: 8px; max width:100%;height:auto;"  />

        
    </figure>



    <figure class="center" >
        <img src="/images/twST03.jpg"   style="border-radius: 8px; max width:100%;height:auto;"  />

        
    </figure>



    <figure class="center" >
        <img src="/images/twST04.jpg"   style="border-radius: 8px; max width:100%;height:auto;"  />

        
    </figure>



    <figure class="center" >
        <img src="/images/twST05.jpg"   style="border-radius: 8px; max width:100%;height:auto;"  />

        
    </figure>

</p>

    <figure class="center" >
        <img src="/images/twMG10.jpg"  alt="Ohio and Isya taking a break from all the walking by taking a picture in front of mirror"   style="border-radius: 8px; max-width:100%;height:auto;"  />

        
            <figcaption class="center"  style="color: 297298;" >Checking traffic</figcaption>
        
    </figure>


]]></content>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>Taiwan Trip, June 2019, (Part 1 of 2)</title>
            <link>/posts/taiwan-part1/</link>
            <pubDate>Sun, 21 Jul 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            
            <guid>/posts/taiwan-part1/</guid>
            <description>5W, 1H of it The last week of October 2018, Gab (Isyaâ€™s sister) and Merci (Isyaâ€™s mother) went to Taipei, Taiwan to attend Gabâ€™s first international group exhibit. Aside from that, they took the trip as a break from their usual routines in Manila and Dumaguete.
Their five-day stay in Taipei, Taiwan did not bring any actual â€œpasalubongâ€ or take-home gifts, but they had a lot of stories and memorable experiences to share with us, me and Ohio.</description>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2 id="5w-1h-of-it">5W, 1H of it</h2>
<p>The last week of October 2018, Gab (Isyaâ€™s sister) and Merci (Isyaâ€™s mother) went to Taipei, Taiwan to attend Gabâ€™s first international group exhibit. Aside from that, they took the trip as a break from their usual routines in Manila and Dumaguete.</p>
<p>Their five-day stay in Taipei, Taiwan did not bring any actual â€œpasalubongâ€ or take-home gifts, but they had a lot of stories and memorable experiences to share with us, me and Ohio. We were enamored by their first hand experience and intrigued by their descriptions of what Taipei is for them. Gab describes it as a mini-chill Japan, and a city filled with trees. It had such a huge impact on her that made her want to study Mandarin. That gave us the impression that Taiwan is worth visiting.</p>
<p>Good thing that for Filipinos wanting to experience Taiwan, it is not difficult since we are granted visa-free entry until the end of July 2019. (Update: As of writing, the <a href="https://www.taiwannews.com.tw/en/news/3721553">visa-free entry has been extended until 2020</a>).</p>
<p>Ohio had just gotten his first ever Philippine Passport that he intends to use for his (limited) travel tendencies. Now, he doesn&rsquo;t blame others if they hadn&rsquo;t had the chance to use theirs outside of a legal documentation of their existence. Perhaps their circumstances prevent them the luxury of traveling abroad, and whatnot. He hopes not to ever get stuck in one place, is what he had always wished for himself.</p>
<p>Of course, it started with an idea from a different field of interest. Ohio was watching <a href="https://invidio.us/watch?v=gNtxiZJ-jQE">a video of The Verge</a> regarding the <a href="https://www.theverge.com/2018/12/6/18125461/must-have-apps-hopper-halide-splitwise-dark-sky-google-photos">apps</a> they love to recommend, and the first app that they mentioned was Hopper. It lets you find and track low-price flights and hotels. He downloaded it and gave it a try.</p>
<p>Hopper&rsquo;s landing page greeted the user with two blank spaces in which to put a starting point (Manila, no less!) and destination. In the many endpoints on the globe&rsquo;s surface, we limited our considerations to budget and distance.</p>
<p>It was January; Year 2019, and Ohioâ€™s mind wandered, and always has been prone to going off tangent. The significant portion his childhood consists of meshing daydreams with studies of reality&hellip; Anyway, Ohioâ€™s thought of visiting Hanoi; or Bangkok wouldn&rsquo;t be so bad as a first international flight for him; or would the traffic conditions in Jakarta be as bad as he hear they say it to be? He thought all of this, and other Southeast Asian countries and typed their capitals in the Hopper, checking for prices and availability.</p>
<p>When Ohio consulted Isya for her opinion, her response was immediate, as sure as she always is. &ldquo;Let&rsquo;s go to Taiwan!&rdquo; she said. At the time of planning, Taiwan had granted Visa-free entry for Philippine passport holders up to July 2019. We wanted to hop on this opportunity which only made sense to choose to travel to Taiwan. Everything clicked all right.</p>
<p>We tried looking for the cheapest flight to Taipei, Taiwan and chanced upon Cebu Pacific, with the help of Hopper. The two-way ticket for the both us, cost around Php 15,000. It was the basic fare offered with no check-in luggage and no meals. We also decided to forego add-ons like preferred seat and insurance. It was Ohioâ€™s idea that we purchase travel insurance from other insurance company named <a href="https://www.chubbtravelinsurance.com.ph/">Chubb</a> that has a more comprehensive benefit, in case something unfortunate happened to us abroad.</p>
<p>With enough savings in our pockets, we booked a trip to Taiwan. We were giddy about the whole trip because it was our first trip together abroad and it was Ohioâ€™s first international trip.</p>
<p>It is also worth mentioning that the biggest factor, after all, that drove the idea to travel this year 2019, was to celebrate Isya&rsquo;s 30th birthday in some other country. An important enough of a milestone deserves a memorable itinerary, which we will share in a moment.</p>
<h2 id="processing-the-preparation">Processing the Preparation</h2>
<p>It was January 2019. Your mornings and nights might have been different from one another, yet when we refer back to our mental notes, nothing out of the blue rocked any of us. The same unimportant people were seated on important seats. The struggle had to beat on to remind us of the singular goal we all should move to. But we were plotting an escape, a temporary one, Isya and I, to remind us that there are other places, too, where we could move to, and possibly learn from. She had just booked a flight for the two of us to Taiwan, scheduled on her birth week.</p>
<blockquote>
<h3 id="advertisement">ADVERTISEMENT</h3>
<p>This segment is brought to you by the nugget of wisdom of one Anita Desai. She said, &ldquo;Wherever you go becomes a part of you somehow.&rdquo; In immersing ourselves, albeit for only a week, in the atmosphere of Taipei, Taiwan, we hope that we had grasped something from its people and culture to take and share back home.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>When we decided on the date and purchased the ticket, the next practical thing to do would be to find a place to stay. We asked for recommendations, from relatives to friends to what would be the best option. It seemed that AirBnB was the obvious choice. It was not an easy process to find a place that we both would agree to. We considered things including budget, proximity to both bus and MRT stations. Also, is it a crowded area? Is it noisy in the neighborhood? Does it have a shared bathroom? Would we be alone in the place, or if not, would we have at least our own room? For every place I found that I thought would fit our wants and needs, I consulted Ohio to get his opinion and yes to the place.</p>
<p>The first AirBnB house we said yes to isnâ€™t in the usual touristy area, nor does environment looked busy. It was on a hill, and we had the entire place for ourselves â€“ our own kitchen, bathroom, and even lavatory. The AirBnB was in Daâ€™an District. We were excited and made our itinerary based on the place we booked.</p>
<p>We booked our flight 6 months before the actual travel, thatâ€™s why we never bothered and worried that much of our confirmed reservation. Alas, come May our host cancelled our reservation due to a personal emergency. This disappointed us in that we would never get to experience the place. Plus, we had to look for another place in such a short time.</p>
<p>The second time we had to look for a place proved to be a harder task, and options were limited, many of which cost higher and in locations that we initially disliked. We tried hard to find a place in the same district as the first one. It was Ohio, who was able to chance upon this bedroom-only, shared bath, and within our budget also located in Daâ€™an. The catch was the minimum stay is 7 nights; we were there for only 6 nights total. We tried looking at the other options but ultimately opted for what Ohio found, because it was cheaper than the rest, and found at decent-looking location.</p>
<p>We only got serious in doing our itinerary, days before our set travel date. So, how does one exactly make a memorable itinerary? We don&rsquo;t know. That&rsquo;s why during the waiting period, we asked our friends and family for suggestions. We also watched travel vlogs, read other seminal wanderers&rsquo; travel diaries, and even did our own due diligence, dude. But to have a proper itinerary from the culmination of information these multiple sources provided, we had to narrow them down, applying whatever constraints we set up ourselves in. We, creatives that we think we are, thought it would be more sanguine if we came up with our own versions, to be fact-checked together when we&rsquo;re done.</p>

    <figure class="center" >
        <img src="/images/tw-itinerary.png"  alt="Itinerary in excel sheet"   style="border-radius: 8px; max-width:100%;height:auto;"  />

        
            <figcaption class="center"  style="color: 297298;" >How our itinerary looked like</figcaption>
        
    </figure>


<p>The central idea behind the making of both versions of itinerary relied on the location of the booked AirBnB. This meant that the first few locations that we&rsquo;d like to explore must be within walking distance, then venturing outwards the Da&rsquo;an District, further as the week progresses.</p>
<p>The itinerary was a mish-mash of recommendations from relatives and friends plus from our own research. We definitely work hard for wonder filled itinerary. Ohio and I had our task of creating a 7-day itinerary that we would both enjoy. We had written on Google sheet with the details of places, how to get there, coordinates, where to eat. For my part, I was so much into details that Ohio warned me that the itinerary should not be rigid.</p>
<p>The <em>final</em> draft of our Taipei Itinerary was completed only days before the actual trip. And by &lsquo;completed&rsquo;, I meant we had only planned for the first three days. We agreed that we would finish the schedule on Taipei itself. A fun way to procrastinate, sure, but there were no real crippling deadlines, so we allowed ourselves this. Alas, once we got there, we ditched the itinerary. Looking back on it now, its demise liberated us with Lao Tzu&rsquo;s timeless wit: &ldquo;A good traveler has no fixed plans and is not intent on arriving.&rdquo;</p>
<p>A day before our trip, Isya decided to buy extra luggage because we each had 7 kg of carry-on. As most of you know, Isya thinks she has a <em>tita</em> body syndrome: which means not carrying heavy bags at her â€œage.â€ She purchased a 20 kgs additional weight and we were able to bring a small luggage with wheel (ah, the convenience). The additional luggage costs us an additional expense of PhP 2,000.00 &ndash; for Isya, it was worth the extra spending for comfort and evade backache. It would have cost much more if one of us got back injured.  ðŸ˜…</p>
<h2 id="actual-travel-and-impressions">Actual Travel and Impressions</h2>
<h3 id="day-1">Day 1</h3>
<p>We set out early on the breaking dawn of 13th of January. We thought that we might be able to take the P2P (point-to-point) bus, but our flight was too early for the first bus scheduled to depart Quezon City. We had no choice but to take the convenient (but overpriced) Grab.  Although our flight was at 7:20 am, we allotted three hours of travel time,  considering the hellscape of Manila traffic. We were wrong, though, as traffic at those wee hours in the morning were relatively light and not a hassle.</p>

    <figure class="center" >
        <img src="/images/tw01.jpg"  alt="A hallway with a push door at the end. Sunlight pours from the windows on the left side."   style="border-radius: 8px; max-width:100%;height:auto;"  />

        
            <figcaption class="center"  style="color: 297298;" >Boarding time</figcaption>
        
    </figure>



    <figure class="center" >
        <img src="/images/tw02.jpg"  alt="Two people, smiling. One man, one woman, both of them amid their existential crisis. The man, in his mid 20s, is holding a coffee in disposable paper cup."   style="border-radius: 8px; max-width:100%;height:auto;"  />

        
            <figcaption class="center"  style="color: 297298;" >Delinquent Duo</figcaption>
        
    </figure>



    <figure class="center" >
        <img src="/images/tw03.jpg"  alt="Overcast weather by the airport runway."   style="border-radius: 8px; max-width:100%;height:auto;"  />

        
            <figcaption class="center"  style="color: 297298;" >Overcast weather by the airport runway.</figcaption>
        
    </figure>


<p>Coming from Manila&rsquo;s daily traffic congestion, the efficiency of Taipei&rsquo;s transportation system is a welcoming shock. Pedestrians need not to race against time when crossing streets, as most motorists know to obey traffic rules. While there are still rude drivers, they are a minority, at least from what we have observed.</p>
<p>Fuyang lane in Da&rsquo;an District, where we booked our stay for one week, seemed an ideal neighborhood: few people, few motorists, serene. Not to mention there is an Eco Park well within strolling distance.</p>
<p>We had a great afternoon walk after checking in at our AirBnB. It was a mini exploration of the neighborhood. One of the nearest â€œtouristyâ€ place in the neighborhood is the Fuyang Eco Park which, arguably,  cannot be explored in one day. Still, the willing ear could almost hear the clatter of species in such green space, if it&rsquo;s patient to distill the wind for their sounds. Otherwise, the slopes, the signs, even the trees sometimes, lead the way. The legs only have to follow the path of least resistance, but such cannot always be the case. It&rsquo;s a good kind of fatigue, in our opinion, to be in the humbling presence of sentinel trees. When we visit again, we will try going to the cicadasâ€™ area to hear their daily hymn.</p>

    <figure class="center" >
        <img src="/images/tw21.jpeg"  alt="A woman in blue shirt with tub hat, smiling. Forest flora surrounds her."   style="border-radius: 8px; max-width:100%;height:auto;"  />

        
            <figcaption class="center"  style="color: 297298;" >Isya in Fuyang Eco Park</figcaption>
        
    </figure>



    <figure class="center" >
        <img src="/images/tw05.jpg"  alt="Two different feet stepping on a tile"   style="border-radius: 8px; max-width:100%;height:auto;"  />

        
            <figcaption class="center"  style="color: 297298;" >Somewhere in the entrance to Fuyang Eco Park</figcaption>
        
    </figure>



    <figure class="left" >
        <img src="/images/tw06.jpg"  alt="A man in blue shirt, treading up a pathway in the forest"   style="border-radius: 8px; max-width:100%;height:auto;"  />

        
            <figcaption class="center"  style="color: 297298;" >A pathway</figcaption>
        
    </figure>



    <figure class="left" >
        <img src="/images/tw07.jpg"  alt="Stony steps in the forest that lead up to somewhere"   style="border-radius: 8px; max-width:100%;height:auto;"  />

        
            <figcaption class="center"  style="color: 297298;" >Stony steps in the forest that lead up to somewhere</figcaption>
        
    </figure>



    <figure class="center" >
        <img src="/images/tw08.jpg"  alt="A man&#39;s silhouette. He is looking over Taipei 101."   style="border-radius: 8px; max-width:100%;height:auto;"  />

        
            <figcaption class="center"  style="color: 297298;" >Looking over Taipei 101</figcaption>
        
    </figure>



    <figure class="center" >
        <img src="/images/tw23.jpeg"  alt="An arch made of forest leaves, under which, a woman poses for picture."   style="border-radius: 8px; max-width:100%;height:auto;"  />

        
            <figcaption class="center"  style="color: 297298;" >Archway made up of forest leaves</figcaption>
        
    </figure>


<p>The park also offered a view of the famous Taipei 101. It was a rainy and cloudy on our first day in Taiwan that a glimpse of the towering structure left us in awe. The experience at the park in a city has offered us what we can only hope or wish for Manila â€“ the balance between greens (nature) and concrete.</p>
<p>Our continued exploration of the neighborhood made us wander to the nearest convenience store just a block away from our AirBnB. Interesting that itâ€™s the same 7/11 we have in the Philippines, but with more and better selection of milk tea and coffee. We can say at this point that Isya is addicted to milk tea while Ohio on the other hand has gusto for drinking coffee. We did not spare any second in trying out local milk tea and coffee products found at the convenience store.  Other perks of having to drink these delicious beverages also include Ohioâ€™s observation that many of the receipts (that had accumulated during the trip) have dimensions thatplay around 50mm x 75mm (2&rdquo; x 3&rdquo;). Little info is printed on the paper, except for the amount you paid for the goods/services, and some QR codes that you can scan for more details. This tactic is definitely a nod to needing less paper and ink, but going digital doesn&rsquo;t necessarily mean going green. Moreover, Isya also observed that these receipts serve as raffle tickets to what game, we donâ€™t know. We wish we knew how to read some of the characters on the receipt that might have given us a clue on how to join and what the prizes are.  ðŸ˜‰</p>

    <figure class="center" >
        <img src="/images/tw20.jpeg"  alt="receipts laid out randomly on a table"   style="border-radius: 8px; max-width:100%;height:auto;"  />

        
            <figcaption class="center"  style="color: 297298;" >Receipts</figcaption>
        
    </figure>


<p>We capped of our day with beef noodles and sayote tops cooked in sesame oil. It wasnâ€™t an easy feat getting that tasty beef noodles because we got lost in all the foreign characters written on the order sheet. We were reluctant to speak lest we miscommunicate our intentions. If there were a competition for shy couples in a trip abroad, we think we would take the grand prize for The Shyest Pair.</p>

    <figure class="center" >
        <img src="/images/tw10.jpg"  alt="A street of Da&#39;an District at Night"   style="border-radius: 8px; max-width:100%;height:auto;"  />

        
    </figure>



    <figure class="center" >
        <img src="/images/tw11.jpg"  alt="A street of Da&#39;an District at Night"   style="border-radius: 8px; max-width:100%;height:auto;"  />

        
    </figure>



    <figure class="center" >
        <img src="/images/tw12.jpg"  alt="A street of Da&#39;an District at Night"   style="border-radius: 8px; max-width:100%;height:auto;"  />

        
    </figure>


<h3 id="day-2">Day 2</h3>
<p>On our second day, we ditched our itinerary and decided to go where itâ€™s convenient with the light rain and overcast weather. We went out to immerse ourselves in the grandiose of Chiang Kai-Shek Memorial Hall.  The landmark houses the National Theater, National Concert Hall, and the main building that houses the huge monument of Chang Kai-Shek.  A spectacle we witnessed was the changing of honor guards.  Isya felt like the guards themselves were in deep meditation, as their synchronised movements require complete concentration and precision. Likewise, the choreography amazed Ohio, but he zoned out in the middle of the routine.  We wondered, â€œDoes Chiang Kai-Shek even appreciate the hourly show of changing guards?â€</p>

    <figure class="center" >
        <img src="/images/twC01.jpg"  alt="A stolen shot of Ohio in the main gate Chiang Kai Shek&#39;s Memorial Hall"   style="border-radius: 8px; max-width: 100%; height:auto:"  />

        
            <figcaption class="center"  style="color: 297298;" > Ohio and the Gate of Great Centrality and Perfect Uprightness</figcaption>
        
    </figure>



    <figure class="center" >
        <img src="/images/twC02.jpg"  alt="View of the Chiang Kai Shek Park"   style="border-radius: 8px; max-width: 100%; height:auto:"  />

        
            <figcaption class="center"  style="color: 297298;" > Chiang Kai Shek Park</figcaption>
        
    </figure>


<!-- raw HTML omitted -->

    <figure class="center" >
        <img src="/images/tw13.jpg"  alt="Inside Chiang Kai Shek&#39;s Main Memorial hall, his large bronze statue smiles at the visitors as they enter"   style="border-radius: 8px; max-width:100%;height:auto;"  />

        
            <figcaption class="center"  style="color: 297298;" >Inside CHK Main Memorial Hall</figcaption>
        
    </figure>


<!-- raw HTML omitted -->

    <figure class="center" >
        <img src="/images/twC03.jpg"  alt=" Native pine trees of Taiwan and home to nimble creatures like squirrels"   style="border-radius:8px; max-width:100%;heaight:auto;"  />

        
            <figcaption class="center"  style="color: 297298;" >Isya among the towering and nimble creatures</figcaption>
        
    </figure>


<p>Digesting Chang Kai-Shekâ€™s life and works made us hungry that after the slow tour we did by ourselves, we headed out in search for a place to eat. In its large complex area, we discovered a forested area at the back of the Memorial Hall, replete with different types of pine trees. More interestingly, tiny, nimble creatures live in the tiny forest â€“ squirrels. They populate the area and are not afraid to get close to visitors.</p>
<p>Our search for a place to eat continued. After walking a few wide blocks away from the complex. There were a lot of cafÃ© and pastry shop, but we wanted a heavy meal to fuel us for the rest of the day. We had our fill at this Japanese fast food restaurant, Sukiya, that specializes in curry dishes.  After filling, and having a breather from all the walking, we strode again and went to explore efficient metro rail transit.</p>
<!-- raw HTML omitted -->

    <figure class="center" >
        <img src="/images/tw15.jpg"  alt="Bowls of rice and curry with miso soup"   style="border-radius: 8px; max-width:100%;height:auto;"  />

        
            <figcaption class="center"  style="color: 297298;" >The only fitting meal for exhausted travelers</figcaption>
        
    </figure>



    <figure class="center" >
        <img src="/images/tw14.jpg"  alt="A building facade in Taipei"   style="border-radius: 8px; max-width:100%;height:auto;"  />

        
            <figcaption class="center"  style="color: 297298;" >That aesthetic</figcaption>
        
    </figure>



    <figure class="center" >
        <img src="/images/tw16.jpg"  alt="A cat statue, black and white, with yellow eyes. Paws are up on its face, as if in shock or disbelief."   style="border-radius: 8px; max-width:100%;height:auto;"  />

        
            <figcaption class="center"  style="color: 297298;" >lol</figcaption>
        
    </figure>



    <figure class="center" >
        <img src="/images/tw17.jpg"  alt="Red House"   style="border-radius: 8px; max-width:100%;height:auto;"  />

        
            <figcaption class="center"  style="color: 297298;" >Red House</figcaption>
        
    </figure>



    <figure class="center" >
        <img src="/images/tw18.jpg"  alt="A busy street"   style="border-radius: 8px; max-width:100%;height:auto;"  />

        
    </figure>



    <figure class="center" >
        <img src="/images/tw19.jpg"  alt="An art installation: a big shoe installed on a mural. Underneath it is a walkway, where people pass through."   style="border-radius: 8px; max-width:100%;height:auto;"  />

        
    </figure>


<!-- raw HTML omitted -->
<p>Another landmark worth visiting is the Red House found at the heart of one of Taipeiâ€™s shopping districts. Despite what its namesake implies, it has nothing to do with prostitution. Itâ€™s just literally red because of the bricks used for its structure. The Red House provides a market for local creatives where they can sell their arts and crafts. Inquisitive that Isya is, all the arts and crafts that she saw evoked feelings &ndash; feelings best explained by her exaltation <em>oohs</em> and <em>ahhs</em>. Ohio, on the other hand, would comment how it would be â€œan unnecessary purchase.â€ We didn&rsquo;t buy anything, though.</p>
<p>It&rsquo;s good, sometimes, to have a flexible itinerary, to give time to breathe, to give ourselves the chance to change the direction of steps, to explore the districts with or without access to internet.</p>
<p>Taipei boasts of extensive night markets scattered around the city, where you can eat different foods and buy stuff you might or might not need. The first night market we went to was the Ningxia Night Market, and it can host a train of people. One may want to quicken their pace, unless they find the smell of stinky tofu pleasant. We dipped our hands on grilled large mushrooms, watermelon juice, and red bean with custard pastry. This is one of the lowkey night markets in Taipei, yet is frequented by locals.</p>
<p>The whole trip we made whopping 23k steps. Fatigue finally kicked us in once we got back to the guesthouse and saw our bed. <code>-o)-</code></p>
<p><em>Continue to <a href="/posts/taiwan-part2/">Part 2</a></em>&hellip;</p>
]]></content>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>The Imperfect Narrative of Repairing an iPod Classic 160GB</title>
            <link>/posts/repair-ipod/</link>
            <pubDate>Wed, 10 Jul 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            
            <guid>/posts/repair-ipod/</guid>
            <description>It is well known in practice that repair of a failed item may not yield a functioning item which is &amp;ldquo;as good as new.&amp;rdquo; Brown, Mark, and Frank Proschan. &amp;ldquo;Imperfect repair.&amp;quot; Journal of Applied probability 20.4 (1983): 851-859.
 In our opinion, repairing broken things is a noble undertaking for anyone who is looking to reduce the waste we send to our landfills. In this world filled with people who breaks things, a repair-person is in demand, nay, GOLD.</description>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[
    <figure class="center" >
        <img src="/images/ipod7.jpg"  alt="an iPod Classic, color grey"   style="border-radius: 8px; max-width:100%;height:auto;"  />

        
    </figure>


<blockquote>
<h4 id="it-is-well-known-in-practice-that-repair-of-a-failed-item-may-not-yield-a-functioning-item-which-is-as-good-as-new">It is well known in practice that repair of a failed item may not yield a functioning item which is &ldquo;as good as new.&rdquo;</h4>
<p>Brown, Mark, and Frank Proschan. <em>&ldquo;Imperfect repair.&quot;</em> Journal of Applied probability 20.4 (1983): 851-859.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>In our opinion, repairing broken things is a noble undertaking for anyone who is looking to reduce the waste we send to our landfills. In this world filled with people who breaks things, a repair-person is in demand, nay, GOLD. (It&rsquo;s worth noting that a different person is tapped to help broken people.)</p>
<p>We should take note, however, that in order to achieve true sustainability, we must follow its top capital R&rsquo;s in <em>this</em> order: Refuse, Reduce, Reuse, Repair, Rot, Recycle, and Rethink. You&rsquo;ll notice that Repair is only fourth in order of importance, but important nonetheless.</p>
<h2 id="what-would-be-the-problem-if-the-item-repaired-isnt-as-good-as-new">What would be the problem if the item repaired isn&rsquo;t as good as new?</h2>
<p>It depends.</p>
<p>If the item is required to measure something, did repairing it restore its original calibrations? Did it improve or worsen? How do we even know if the output is accurate if the device itself <em>could</em> be inaccurate starting at the time of failure? There are more questions to be answered before and after a repair, and the answers to each depend on the complexity of the problem and the technical expertise of the handyman. Indeed, learning about proper diagnostics and troubleshooting are important skills to learn for a repairman of any trade.</p>
<p>As a kid, Ohio disassembled toy radios with a Philips screwdriver and examined the circuit board within, not really knowing what each part was for. Everything then looked foreign, but it&rsquo;s in those moments that the Unknown became awesome.</p>
<p>The act of repairing isn&rsquo;t a revelation. It&rsquo;s a natural reaction, a sort of problem-solving tool, to anything broken, or are prone to breaking. Just look at the small stalls, formal or informal, by the streets that are more than capable to fix your watch, umbrella, shoes, electric fans, washing machines, televisions, refrigerators, etc.</p>
<p>Today, anyone can begin learning how to repair broken stuff. While technical expertise helps, a quick search in YouTube for repair tutorials will yield that many of them are created by people enthused by the prospect of helping others repair their own things. If, you think the proper tools matter, why, yes, they do, but some of them can be borrowed from your friend or neighbor.</p>
<h2 id="now-the-ipod">Now, the iPod</h2>
<p>This recent fascination lead me to hound for broken things to practice my novice repair skills with. I had no specific rubric with which to refer to when it comes to what exact kinds of things to fix, but I guess the main driver would be, repairing it would bring its functionality back and add value (again) to life.</p>
<p>In my search, I saw Isya&rsquo;s iPod tucked away in a drawer, unused, almost forgotten. I asked her immediately what was its problem.</p>
<p>It wasn&rsquo;t turning on, even when we tried plugging it to a power source. She also vaguely recalled that she might have rolled over it.</p>

    <figure class="center" >
        <img src="/images/ipod8.jpeg"  alt="snippet from a Neistat video, with the text: iPod&#39;s UNREPLACEABLE battery lasts only 18 months"   style="border-radius: 8px; max-width:100%;height:auto;"  />

        
            <figcaption class="center"  style="color: 297298;" >(c) Neistat Brothers</figcaption>
        
    </figure>


<p>I remember watching a <a href="https://invidio.us/watch?v=SuTcavAzopg">Casey and Van Neistat video</a> that went viral in the early naught&rsquo;s, titled &ldquo;iPod&rsquo;s Dirty Secret&rdquo;. It exposed that &ldquo;iPOD&rsquo;S UNREPLACEABLE [sic] BATTERY LASTS ONLY 18 MONTHS&rdquo;. At the time, to refurbish the iPod with a bust battery, the owner would have to send it back to Apple&rsquo;s Customer Service and pay around US$ 250. At that price, why not just get a new one?</p>
<p>This Apple behavior should not surprise anyone. Apple is still screwing over their customers today by continuously blocking third-party repairs, and also lobby against Right to Repair legislation currently being put forward in the US. That&rsquo;s why it&rsquo;s better to &ldquo;take advantage&rdquo; of their devices that are still repairable. One of them, fortunately is this iPod.</p>
<p>This business strategy, though, isn&rsquo;t exclusive (shocking!) to Apple&rsquo;s iPods, nor to Apple (even more shocking!), for that matter. In the time of Thomas Edison, incandescent light bulbs&rsquo; filament was changed from carbon to tungsten &ndash; the latter being thinner than the former, and thus cheaper to reproduce &ndash; so that selling them had become more profitable because of planned obsolescence. We&rsquo;re sure there&rsquo;d be more of them now and in the future, as people seem to idolize the likes of both Steve Jobs and Thomas Edison, &ldquo;innovators&rdquo; that they were.</p>
<p>Many other companies continue to sell their products with planned obsolescence. This means that the product &ndash; in many of them, electronic device &ndash; is designed to break down after a few years of regular use. Worse, when they do break down, it&rsquo;s constructed to be difficult to open. They also don&rsquo;t share the repair manual. If one did manage to open it, the parts are either glued together (so that picking them apart is difficult), attached to the case with incompatible screws, or their replacements are hard to find.</p>
<h2 id="isyas-ipod----an-interstitial">Isya&rsquo;s iPod &ndash; an interstitial</h2>
<p>When Isya&rsquo;s sister won grand prize for an art competition, she (the sister) gave Isya an iPod Classic (what is now known as 7th gen) as a gift. Although it was only recently that I found out about its origins, the sentimental value only reinforced the need for my restoring it.</p>
<h2 id="what-happened-next">What Happened Next</h2>
<p>So, amid the lull between bid-thee-well and borrow, Isya was convinced to let her iPod Classic have an overhaul. This was after the research had already been conducted on the matter, what parts to buy, what tools to pry it with, and so on.</p>
<p>At the outset, it&rsquo;s important to have a guide one can work with, unless one has the natural wits to deal with a complex electronic device. The starting point for this project was <a href="https://invidio.us/watch?v=4AF1Pjbwc6c">Geek Detour&rsquo;s video</a>. It&rsquo;s informative as well as entertaining. Everson Siqueira, the channel&rsquo;s host, also details what he did wrong, so the viewers can learn from his mistakes.</p>
<h2 id="the-repair-process">The Repair Process</h2>
<p>Here&rsquo;s the list of things bought online:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.iflash.xyz/store/iflash-quad/">iFlash-Quad microSD Adapter</a>. This Solid State Drive (SSD) would replace the old onboard Hard Disk Drive (HDD), requiring less battery usage while improving loading speed.</li>
<li>Special prying tool for iPod Classic. This is also listed in the iFlash store.</li>
<li>MicroSD Cards. Look for the info listed on iFlash site as to what cards would work well with the adapter. At the time of this writing, we bought two (2) pcs of Lexar 64GB microSD cards. There are two (2) remaining slots, which we might use some time in the future.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.ebay.ph/itm/Replacement-battery-for-ipod-classic-7th-gen-generation-160GB-650mAh-thin/223227260913">New Battery</a></li>
</ul>
<p>The original plan was to have the iPod up and running again before our first international trip together, scheduled on mid-June 2019. We would stock-pile on playlists and listen to them on the plane for the two-something hours of flight to Taipei.</p>
<p>Of course, we junked that plan in quiet unison. The role of the iPod, while it has surfaced, had not been fully realized, not with its upgrade parts still not coming together. My reasons for not facing this project for some time now should be incredible, and some of them, familial in nature, <em>are</em>; however, it took a few more weeks past our Taiwan travel before I, a self-appointed repair-person, got to finally sit down with the tools and parts and do what I had been intending to do in months before.</p>
<p>If we were to include in the process the time we had to wait for the items to be delivered, then this whole fiasco lasted about three months, including the time Ohio spent in lethargic limbo. Life happens, and sometimes things get less exciting even on those we thought we&rsquo;re truly passionate about.</p>
<p>Upgrading Isya&rsquo;s iPod turned out to be a success, of course, but as the title implies, the state in which it has been put in now is below standard. Look:</p>

    <figure class="center" >
        <img src="/images/ipod1.jpg"  alt="an iPod Classic, color grey"   style="border-radius: 8px; max-width:100%;height:auto;"  />

        
    </figure>



    <figure class="center" >
        <img src="/images/ipod2.jpg"  alt="an iPod Classic, color grey"   style="border-radius: 8px; max-width:100%;height:auto;"  />

        
    </figure>



    <figure class="center" >
        <img src="/images/ipod3.jpg"  alt="an iPod Classic, color grey"   style="border-radius: 8px; max-width:100%;height:auto;"  />

        
    </figure>



    <figure class="center" >
        <img src="/images/ipod5.jpg"  alt="an iPod Classic, color grey"   style="border-radius: 8px; max-width:100%;height:auto;"  />

        
    </figure>



    <figure class="center" >
        <img src="/images/ipod6.jpg"  alt="an iPod Classic, color grey"   style="border-radius: 8px; max-width:100%;height:auto;"  />

        
    </figure>


<p>We can&rsquo;t figure out what&rsquo;s blocking the components inside, preventing a complete close of the back panel. It could be brute-forced to close, but we reckon this might damage the LCD screen, or pierce the battery, or what-have-you. We&rsquo;d like to think that we did all the steps correctly, but Isya commented that it could be that the battery used was an ill fit for the the iPod.</p>
<p>A proper repair guy would retrace the steps he did to figure out what went wrong where, but I think troubleshooting is better saved for the future as a separate endeavor.</p>
<p>But it isn&rsquo;t stupid if it works, right? This iPod lives on, then. <code>-o)-</code></p>
]]></content>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>How to post a blog here (META)</title>
            <link>/posts/arawflow/</link>
            <pubDate>Sun, 30 Aug 2020 14:53:26 +0800</pubDate>
            
            <guid>/posts/arawflow/</guid>
            <description>Dear Isya,
Last year, we came to an agreement to make a blog that would reflect some of our musings that we can share to the public. Araw Seekers the blog has existed since.
Static Site choice While our first choice was to create one using WordPress, I realized later on that that platform is bloated. So many widgets, plugins, and other applications that we will never use. These unnecessary stuff affect loading times of a site.</description>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Dear Isya,</p>
<p>Last year, we came to an agreement to make a blog that would reflect some of our musings that we can share to the public.
Araw Seekers the blog has existed since.</p>
<h2 id="static-site-choice">Static Site choice</h2>
<p>While our first choice was to create <a href="https://arawseekers.wordpress.com/">one</a> using WordPress, I realized later on that that platform is bloated.
So many widgets, plugins, and other applications that we will never use.
These unnecessary stuff affect loading times of a site.
Since our use case is only a small blog, we ditched the dynamic content management system of big names like WordPress or Blogger, and opted for something called static site generator.</p>
<p>As the name implies, it generates a static site, which you could think of as a &ldquo;traditional&rdquo; websitewhere all content consists of HTML files.
This is good for our use case, because it means faster loading times due to it requiring less processing power.
Not only that, but bloated websites contribute to huge power consumptions in data centers and servers around the world.
Since le Internet is big, one can imagine the implications on our environment.
All the more we should &ldquo;slim down&rdquo; our site.</p>
<p>I picked <a href="https://gohugo.io">Hugo</a> at the time of this site&rsquo;s creation, for no particular reason other than it&rsquo;s supposed to be one of, if not <em>the</em>, fastest static site generators out there.</p>
<h2 id="the-workflow">The Workflow</h2>
<p>Now, I will try to explain the work flow when creating and/or editing a blog entry to be posted here.
Since we will be mainly working on your MacBook Pro, any commands will only consider that environment.</p>
<h3 id="prelims">Prelims</h3>
<p>First, open the following programs:</p>
<ul>
<li>Terminal (where you will type commands later)</li>
<li>Atom, or any text editor (where you will edit the blog entries)</li>
<li>Firefox, or any web browser (where you will view the rendered site)</li>
</ul>
<blockquote>
<p><strong>TIP</strong>: Make use of the Spotlight by pressing <code>âŒ˜ + Space</code>, and start typing the name of the programs above.</p>
</blockquote>
<h3 id="step-1-go-to-our-sites-folder">Step 1: Go to our site&rsquo;s folder</h3>
<p>In the terminal, enter <code>arawseekers</code>.
This is an <em>alias</em> (a shortcut for a command, usually shorter than the original) that will bring you to <code>isyaferrer/Sites/arawseekers/</code> folder.</p>
<h3 id="step-2-create-new-post">Step 2: Create New Post</h3>
<p>If you will edit an existing post, skip this step and proceed to the Step 3.</p>
<p>If you are starting a new entry, enter in the terminal: <code>hugo new content/posts/xyz.md</code>.
Let&rsquo;s break down that command:</p>
<ul>
<li><code>hugo new</code> generates a new, blank post</li>
<li><code>content/posts</code> is the relative folder in which this new file is placed. You can replace this with other folder path, but that&rsquo;s out of the scope (quite literally) of this entry.</li>
<li><code>xyz</code> is the would-be title of the blog post. Although you can edit this later, make it relevant to the post. Mind also the <code>.md</code> (markdown) file extension as this is important.</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="step-3-content-creation">Step 3: Content Creation</h3>
<p>Using the Atom editor, open the file.</p>
<p>The top part is called the front matter.
This is the post&rsquo;s metadata that usually includes the title post, date and time of creation, tags, etc., all of which can be edited.</p>
<p>You can start the blog entry after the front matter.</p>
<pre><code>---
title: &quot;How to post a blog here (META)&quot;
date: 2020-08-30T14:53:26+08:00
draft: false
tags: [&quot;hugo&quot;, &quot;blog&quot;]
---
Dear Isya,

Last year, we came to an agreement to make a blog that would reflect some of our musings that we can share to the public.
Araw Seekers the blog has existed since.
</code></pre>
<p>Now that&rsquo;s meta.</p>
<p>Since you will be editing this in a markdown file, I suggest you <a href="https://www.markdownguide.org/cheat-sheet">familiarize yourself with markdown</a>.</p>
<h4 id="the-small-matter-of-compressing-images">The small matter of compressing images</h4>
<p>As mentioned earlier, static sites load faster.
Usually.
We can maintain this trait by not uploading high quality images.</p>
<p>To compress any image you might include in a post, upload them first in <a href="https://tinyjpg.com">TinyJPG</a>.
You can upload &ldquo;up to 20 images, max 5 MB each&rdquo;.
After compressing all the images, download them all and paste them in <code>isyaferrer/Sites/arawseekers/static/images/</code>.
You can now refer to the images in this folder path.</p>
<blockquote>
<p><strong>TIP</strong>: If you&rsquo;re using the <a href="https://www.privacytools.io/browsers/#addons">hardened Firefox</a>, then you can bypass the 20-image limit of TinyJPG.
Just quit the browser, reopen, and revisit TinyJPG.
This should clear the cookies stored in the browser.
Rinse and repeat as needed.</p>
</blockquote>
<h3 id="step-4-checking-the-content">Step 4: Checking the Content</h3>
<p>Now that you have content, you may want to know how it looks as a blog post.</p>
<p>In the terminal, enter <code>hugo server</code>.
This command renders the site for preview in the browser.
As long as this is running in the terminal, changes made (and saved) in Atom are immediately reflected in the browser, which can be viewed when you enter <code>localhost:1313</code> in the URL bar.</p>
<p>Also, you can&rsquo;t input new commands while this is running in the terminal.
You may want to open a new instance of terminal if you&rsquo;re going to input some new command.</p>
<p>Press <code>control + C</code> to stop the rendering, thus freeing the terminal.</p>
<p>Here&rsquo;s a sample terminal output:</p>
<pre><code>                   | EN   
-------------------+------
Pages            |  47  
Paginator pages  |   0  
Non-page files   |   0  
Static files     | 165  
Processed images |   0  
Aliases          |   6  
Sitemaps         |   1  
Cleaned          |   0  

Built in 744 ms
Watching for changes in /Users/isyaferrer/Sites/arawseekers/{archetypes,assets,content,data,layouts,static,themes}
Watching for config changes in /Users/isyaferrer/Sites/arawseekers/config.toml
Environment: &quot;development&quot;
Serving pages from memory
Running in Fast Render Mode. For full rebuilds on change: hugo server --disableFastRender
Web Server is available at //localhost:1313/ (bind address 127.0.0.1)
Press Ctrl+C to stop
</code></pre>
<p>And here&rsquo;s how it would look like in the browser:</p>

    <figure class="center" >
        <img src="/images/meta.png"  alt="screenshot of the blog"   style="border-radius: 8px; max-width:100%;hei    ght:auto;"  />

        
            <figcaption class="center"  style="color: 297298;" >Now that&#39;s meta.</figcaption>
        
    </figure>


<h3 id="step-5-finalizing-the-content">Step 5: Finalizing the Content</h3>
<p>If you&rsquo;re satisfied with how everything is laid out, you&rsquo;re almost done.</p>
<p>If you haven&rsquo;t yet, press <code>control + C</code> in the terminal to stop the site rendering and to free up the terminal.</p>
<p>Still at the terminal, enter <code>hugo</code>.
This command will create the HTML files and put them all in the <code>isyaferrer/Sites/arawseekers/docs/</code> folder.</p>
<h3 id="step-6-going-live">Step 6: Going Live</h3>
<p>In the terminal, enter <code>arawpush</code>.
It&rsquo;s another alias that invokes a simple shell script that &ldquo;pushes&rdquo; our HTML files from the previous step to the GitHub server, where our blog is currently hosted for free.</p>
<p>The shell script, aptly named <strong>arawpush.sh</strong>, is a file containing a series of commands that accomplish several tasks.</p>
<p>For transparency, here are the commands written in <strong>arawpush.sh</strong>:</p>
<pre><code>#!/bin/sh

git add .
git commit -m &quot;some surprise adds and/or edit/s&quot;
git push -u origin master
</code></pre>
<p>If that doesn&rsquo;t make sense, it&rsquo;s okay. Just enter <code>arawpush</code> in the terminal and it will execute the last three lines of the script without the need to type them all out. <em>Ayos!</em></p>
<h2 id="congrats">Congrats!</h2>
<p>You have shared a new blog post to our two readers!
May we share more together!</p>
<h2 id="parting-thoughts">Parting thoughts</h2>
<p>More than a year after creating this blog, I am realizing that Hugo, too, is a massive tool whose documentation can be confusing, especially for those who aren&rsquo;t too keen on reading them on their free time.
I <em>might</em> consider using a <a href="https://www.romanzolotarev.com/ssg.html">simpler static site generator</a>, but this also means overhauling the site, which neither of us has the time nor the patience to do&hellip; yet.
For now, Hugo will do.</p>
<p>Anyway, I hope you found this informative.
If not, you know where to find me. ;)</p>
<p>xoxo0xox0ox00xxooXX++xx+0+0x+0x,<br>
Ohio</p>
<p><code>-(o-</code></p>
]]></content>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>I Mask, I Mask, I Mask</title>
            <link>/posts/i-mask/</link>
            <pubDate>Mon, 17 Aug 2020 16:05:59 +0800</pubDate>
            
            <guid>/posts/i-mask/</guid>
            <description>Threading Bobbin  We are in a pandemic! Everyone panic or just relax, exercise, drink vitamins, and boost your immune system. There is a need to recognize that not all people have the luxury to just relax and be positive (known today as toxic positivity, but it&amp;rsquo;s mostly just toxic), they have to toil every day to make ends meet and to feed themselves and their family. This pandemic has greatly affected our lives emotionally, mentally, and physically.</description>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[
    <figure class="center" >
        <img src="/images/sinulid-min.gif"  alt="Giling Sinulid"   style="border-radius: 8px; max-width:100%;height:auto;"  />

        
            <figcaption class="center"  style="color: 297298;" >Threading Bobbin</figcaption>
        
    </figure>


<p>We are in a pandemic!
Everyone panic or just relax, exercise, drink vitamins, and boost your immune system.
There is a need to recognize that not all people have the luxury to just relax and be positive (known today as toxic positivity, but it&rsquo;s mostly just toxic), they have to toil every day to make ends meet and to feed themselves and their family.
This pandemic has greatly affected our lives emotionally, mentally, and physically.
It has been difficult to live in times of Uncertainty x Uncertainty = Immense Unquantifiable Uncertainty.
Plus, it <em>helps</em> that the government comes up with nada plan.</p>
<h2 id="keeping-it-sane">Keeping it sane!</h2>
<p>A must-have now at this COVID-19 era is to wear a mask to protect yourself and the people around you.
It&rsquo;s really more about preventing yourself from wreaking havoc on another personâ€™s health, if you happen to carry the virus.</p>
<p>As soon as the news broke that the masks helps mitigate the spreading of virus, the only next practical thing to do is make one.
I started looking into it, especially I have stashed away fabrics for a long time, from unused bedsheets, dresses that no longer fit me nor anyone in my family, to printed fabrics that I bought out of â€œAww, this will good look as blouseâ€ moments.
But I have never touched or snipped even a centimeter of any of it because of the fear that I might not do those fabrics justice.
But this is a monumental moment to be brave and cut the fabrics to create something useful.</p>
<p>I let go of the fear of â€œruiningâ€ my fabrics and just went crazy with making masks.
Chill crazy.</p>
<h2 id="masks-evolution">Masks evolution</h2>
<p>How did I do my masks?</p>
<p>One thing Iâ€™ve learned from my brief stint in fashion school and course in pattern making is that your model can be from what you already have.
<em>Tadah!</em>
A very industrious ingenious idea.</p>
<p>A bit of a side story:
Before all this hullabaloo, there is a country in Southeast Asia that seems to be ahead of their time when it comes to masks (and this is only based on my experience and might not be a fact) and might have been ready even before this pandemic: Vietnam.
They have already made masks accessible and fashionable.
Youâ€™ll see cute masks being peddled on the side streets.</p>
<p>A mask I bought in Vietnam on December 2012 was my first model for pattern.
I got a recycled paper with a clean backside and laid the folded mask.
After making sure that the masks would not move, I began to trace the pattern on the clean paper.
Then added a Â¼ cm seam allowance.
It was a success.</p>

    <figure class="center" >
        <img src="/images/Vietmask2.jpeg"  alt="Mask bought from Vietnam as a souvenir. The outer fabric has print of nuts and woods"   style="border-radius: 8px; max-width:100%;height:auto;"  />

        
            <figcaption class="center"  style="color: 297298;" >Mask from Vietnam: my first pattern model</figcaption>
        
    </figure>


<p>But I did not immediately go into laying my pattern on fabrics.
I needed to consult other references in creating a masks to see whatâ€™s effective.
University of Youtube naturally was the first place to visit.
Luckily, my favorite channel, <a href="https://www.youtube.com/user/madebyaya">madebyaya</a>, released a DIY mask refashion video using old clothes and scrap fabrics.
Once I saw how nice the fit of her mask is, I completely abandoned my self-made pattern.</p>
<p>Watch <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=rUrNjeBnu_U">here</a> if ever you want to create your own mask.</p>
<p>I immediately started creating the mask.
As for all sewing projects, you should first start with a pattern.
I got a scratch paper for my pattern made sure I got the measurement right and draw straight lines.
But with my drawing skills, nothing is ever straight even with the aid of a ruler.</p>

    <figure class="center" >
        <img src="/images/pattern1.jpeg"  alt="Red paper cut on the sides to create pattern for face mask"   style="border-radius: 8px; max-width:100%;height:auto;"  />

        
            <figcaption class="center"  style="color: 297298;" >Here is my pattern and youâ€™ll probably see that its uhmmm not straight. Hahahaha!</figcaption>
        
    </figure>


<p>After 30 mins of figuring out the pattern, I moved on to rummaging my boxes of fabrics to find the right one.
To be honest not all of my fabrics were from old blouses and bedsheets.
I used some of my new-old fabrics now more than 5-10 years old.
(OMG! The fear of using new fabrics is real!)</p>
<p>After so much debating inside my head on what fabrics I would â€œsacrifice,â€ I continued with pinning my pattern to the fabrics.
I cried a little when the scissors started snipping. I had to move on as soon as possible.
In the wise words of Dr. Manhattan:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Creation only happens after destruction.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Wait, this might not be verbatim.</p>

    <figure class="center" >
        <img src="/images/fullsizeoutput_27d2.jpeg"  alt="two fabrics with different size"   style="border-radius: 8px; max-width:100%;height:auto;"  />

        
            <figcaption class="center"  style="color: 297298;" >Ooops, something is wrong with my cut fabrics</figcaption>
        
    </figure>



    <figure class="center" >
        <img src="/images/Mask6.jpeg"  alt="Assembled fabrics ready for sewing"   style="border-radius: 8px; max-width:100%;height:auto;"  />

        
            <figcaption class="center"  style="color: 297298;" >Ready for sewing!</figcaption>
        
    </figure>



    <figure class="center" >
        <img src="/images/Mask5.jpeg"  alt="two fabrics with different size"   style="border-radius: 8px; max-width:100%;height:auto;"  />

        
            <figcaption class="center"  style="color: 297298;" >Almost there and adding the finishing touches.</figcaption>
        
    </figure>


<p>I got over cutting my pretty fabrics and started assembling them.
The first two masks I made was for me and Ohio.
I followed the instruction to the letter, and what I got was a great result.
Although, I did not have any leather straps.
I decided to use thin ribbons first for my mask, and used garter for Ohioâ€™s mask.
This is how they came out.</p>

    <figure class="center" >
        <img src="/images/Mask3.jpeg"  alt="Finished face mask made from jeans or chambray fabric with inner lining of African Textile"   style="border-radius: 8px; max-width:100%;height:auto;"  />

        
            <figcaption class="center"  style="color: 297298;" >Face mask finish product: inside view with tissue paper as filter</figcaption>
        
    </figure>



    <figure class="center" >
        <img src="/images/Mask1.jpeg"  alt="Face mask made of jeans or chambray fabric with ribbons that goes over your ears"   style="border-radius: 8px; max-width:100%;height:auto;"  />

        
            <figcaption class="center"  style="color: 297298;" >Top view of face mask</figcaption>
        
    </figure>


<p>My fans (read: family) liked them.
They all requested that I make one for them, too. I gladly obliged because I was pleased with result of my first masks.
My sister&rsquo;s request is that her mask to have the strings to be tied on the back, which is the better choice because the gartered ones become painful to the ears after wearing them for some time.</p>
<p>
    <figure class="center" >
        <img src="/images/Mask4.jpeg"  alt="Face mask with cat print"   style="border-radius: 8px; max-width:100%;height:auto;"  />

        
            <figcaption class="center"  style="color: 297298;" >Gab 1st face mask</figcaption>
        
    </figure>



    <figure class="center" >
        <img src="/images/fullsizeoutput_27cf.jpeg"  alt="Face mask with orange burst print"   style="border-radius: 8px; max-width:100%;height:auto;"  />

        
            <figcaption class="center"  style="color: 297298;" >Gab 2nd face mask with me modelling</figcaption>
        
    </figure>

</p>
<p>I did not consult any references on how to sew masks with the strings. I experimented on the two masks that I was going to give my sister.
Her feedback would help me construct a better mask, which my mother also requested.</p>
<p>Feedback from user experience was, the mask with cat print did not fit the face well. It did not hold firmly against the side of the face, part of the cheeks. I consulted other videos with tiebacks to understand better construction.
I came across <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=y3lcPRHo_nY">this video</a> which I referred to for adding the ties.
The construction made sense, and I applied it to the masks that I was going to give my mother.
I made her two masks with bright orange pattern and a solid denim fabric with floral ties.</p>
<p>I decided to redo the first prototypes I made for me and Ohio, to ties from garterized ones.</p>
<p>We sent the masks to Dumaguete where my mother is, and she went about using my DIY face masks. Some friends complimented her on how pretty the ones she is using. So, she asked me to create more pieces that she could sell there.
To which I obliged, of course! I donâ€™t know what I was thinking. But it must because I had a good time creating the first batch.
And it was like a welcome challenge.</p>
<p>I did another eight masks; three of which has a different structure.
Another improvement I made was, instead of the ties going over the body of the masks, I inserted them between the right sides of the fabrics.
This technique I got from <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=F5ccDmQWptM">another video by Mister Domestic</a> which I did not get on the first try.
I needed to rip all sides just to correct it.
Getting it right = the best feeling.
So many days have passed, I finally finished the eight additional face masks.
It took that long because I sew only during my free/break time.</p>
<p>Here are the results of my face mask making-spree, and they are currently on their way to Dumaguete.</p>

    <figure class="center" >
        <img src="/images/Mask22.jpeg"  alt="All the face masks I made"   style="border-radius: 8px; max-width:100%;height:auto;"  />

        
            <figcaption class="center"  style="color: 297298;" >Stash of face masks bound for Dumaguete</figcaption>
        
    </figure>



    <figure class="center" >
        <img src="/images/Mask21.jpeg"  alt="Face mask with orange burst print"   style="border-radius: 8px; max-width:100%;height:auto;"  />

        
            <figcaption class="center"  style="color: 297298;" >Different pattern used for this orange burst face mask</figcaption>
        
    </figure>



    <figure class="center" >
        <img src="/images/Mask15.jpeg"  alt="Face mask with cat print on yellow fabric"   style="border-radius: 8px; max-width:100%;height:auto;"  />

        
            <figcaption class="center"  style="color: 297298;" >Cat print face mask</figcaption>
        
    </figure>



    <figure class="center" >
        <img src="/images/Mask12.jpeg"  alt="Face mask with floral print on light blue fabric"   style="border-radius: 8px; max-width:100%;height:auto;"  />

        
            <figcaption class="center"  style="color: 297298;" >Floral fabric face mask</figcaption>
        
    </figure>



    <figure class="center" >
        <img src="/images/Mask8.jpeg"  alt="Solid color dark blue jeans fabric"   style="border-radius: 8px; max-width:100%;height:auto;"  />

        
            <figcaption class="center"  style="color: 297298;" >Jeans fabric face mask</figcaption>
        
    </figure>



    <figure class="center" >
        <img src="/images/Masks.jpeg"  alt="Preparing all the face mask which is bound for Dumaguete"   style="border-radius: 8px; max-width:100%;height:auto;"  />

        
            <figcaption class="center"  style="color: 297298;" >Quality assurance and quality control</figcaption>
        
    </figure>



    <figure class="center" >
        <img src="/images/Mask16.jpeg"  alt="Face masks inside a box"   style="border-radius: 8px; max-width:100%;height:auto;"  />

        
            <figcaption class="center"  style="color: 297298;" >Packing all the face masks</figcaption>
        
    </figure>


<h2 id="parting-thoughts">Parting thoughts</h2>
<p>They say face masks at this time can save you or another person from this pandemic.
It does not hurt to wear a mask, because you know prevention is better than cure.
At this point, it should feel like second skin now.</p>
<p>If your are interested to make your own, it&rsquo;s free to click on the links above.
If you donâ€™t have the tools nor the time to make, write us an email and I can make one for you, for a small reasonable fee, of course..</p>

    <figure class="center" >
        <img src="/images/MaskwIsya.jpeg"  alt="Face mask with orange burst print"   style="border-radius: 8px; max-width:100%;height:auto;"  />

        
            <figcaption class="center"  style="color: 297298;" >I offer you face mask. Keep safe!</figcaption>
        
    </figure>


<p><code>-o)-</code></p>
]]></content>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>Traveling for Work</title>
            <link>/posts/travel-for-work/</link>
            <pubDate>Fri, 10 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            
            <guid>/posts/travel-for-work/</guid>
            <description>Earlier this year, I was (un)lucky enough to be reassigned to the account that I thought I&amp;rsquo;d never be going back to. Only this time around, the assignment&amp;rsquo;s scope is nationwide, as in I got to go to places in different parts of the country where there a project site exists. Meaning, my employer would reimburse my travel expenses as long as they&amp;rsquo;re official business trips.
This is a good time as any, for me at least, to recall these trips, knowing that travel is something I shall not be doing any time soon, until 30 Apr, according to someone.</description>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Earlier this year, I was (un)lucky enough to be reassigned to the account that I thought I&rsquo;d never be going back to.
Only this time around, the assignment&rsquo;s scope is nationwide, as in I got to go to places in different parts of the country where there a project site exists.
Meaning, my employer would reimburse my travel expenses as long as they&rsquo;re official business trips.</p>
<p>This is a good time as any, for me at least, to recall these trips, knowing that travel is something I shall not be doing any time soon, until <a href="https://news.mb.com.ph/2020/04/07/duterte-extends-lockdown-to-april-30/">30 Apr, according to someone</a>.
And to be tethered to the house we choose, to help to flatten the curve, except for the few times that we have to run to the nearest wet market for food supplies.</p>
<p>Anyway, let me put here my travel notes, plus some photos &ndash; ranging from late January to late February &ndash; without mentioning anything work-related, because damn it, I <em>dislike</em> working that much!</p>
<hr>
<h2 id="calasiao-pangasinan">Calasiao, Pangasinan</h2>
<p>Stuck in BD&rsquo;s orange Vios (which by the way, is everywhere these days, ugly as it is) with the U-Team for almost four hours now since we left Quezon City. Since I heard the term, I&rsquo;ve been promoting <em>radical transparency</em> where applicable, but the people of U-Team take it to the next level with their misogyny and sexism! And I was supposed to listen through it without complaining. I shouldn&rsquo;t be surprised, since a DOM leads them with his Boomer machismo. I remained silent throughout AA&rsquo;s (the DOM) yapping. Back in the passenger seat, I was sandwiched between two men&hellip; and I truly hope that doesn&rsquo;t come off as an innuendo. Nothing particularly interesting here.</p>
<hr>
<h2 id="san-fernando-la-union">San Fernando, La Union</h2>

    <figure class="center" >
        <img src="/images/tfw21.jpeg"  alt="inside looking out the beach"   style="border-radius: 8px; max-width:100%;height:auto;"  />

        
            <figcaption class="center"  style="color: 297298;" >The view of the beach from inside the Inn</figcaption>
        
    </figure>


<p>We were booked in an inn called <a href="https://www.agoda.com/the-little-surfmaid-resort/hotel/la-union-ph.html">Little Surf Maid</a>. This is my first beach of the year, and I wouldn&rsquo;t have thought it would be because of some stupid work. In the many establishments that proliferate the beach side, the people of U-Team, headed by AA (who else), chose the most suffocating, un-ventilated, grimy nipa hut to drink <em>one</em> bottle of beer. His taste couldn&rsquo;t be any less succinct. My colleague, AC, agrees that there are a lot of better food out there &ndash; and I know this myself because I explored a little along the street that night alone.</p>

    <figure class="center" >
        <img src="/images/tfw20.jpeg"  alt="sunset by the beach"   style="border-radius: 8px; max-width:100%;height:auto;"  />

        
            <figcaption class="center"  style="color: 297298;" >The dog might have already taken for granted this sunset</figcaption>
        
    </figure>


<hr>
<h2 id="bagacay-dumaguete">Bagacay, Dumaguete</h2>
<p>The only thing worth remembering here is the after-work, of course. The sooner I forget the dayshift, the better. I spent the night sharing good food with Isya&rsquo;s mother, Merci, and her partner, Tito Jorge in a Chinese-filled Chinese bistro (<a href="https://www.tripadvisor.com.ph/Restaurant_Review-g616032-d18893995-Reviews-Halang_Halang_Restaurant-Dumaguete_City_Negros_Oriental_Negros_Island_Visayas.html"><em>Halang Halang</em></a> it is called). This was also around the time when nCoV-19 was making its rounds offshore, still a whisper away. Before our orders even came, a power interruption made the night, uh, spicier, more than the food, even more so than the Chinese people who were relentlessly coughing and sneezing nearby. The brownout experience, though, was redeemed by their great food.</p>
<hr>
<h3 id="interstitial">INTERSTITIAL</h3>

    <figure class="center" >
        <img src="/images/tfw13.jpeg"  alt="bird&#39;s eyeview of a mountain"   style="border-radius: 8px; max-width:100%;height:auto;"  />

        
            <figcaption class="center"  style="color: 297298;" >I think this is Mount Kanlaon?</figcaption>
        
    </figure>


<p>In travels involving flights, I made it a point to at least give the scene below some looking. With my limited knowledge on local geography (yes to Pinoy Pride!), I can&rsquo;t always figure out what place I am on top of. It doesn&rsquo;t help that I&rsquo;m no navigator, nor a traveller with a sense of direction. But I&rsquo;m working on all of that. Meanwhile, that mountain ridge, though&hellip;</p>
<hr>
<h2 id="laoag-ilocos-norte">Laoag, Ilocos Norte</h2>

    <figure class="center" >
        <img src="/images/tfw10.jpeg"  alt="building facade with a sign saying Ilocos Norte Capitol"   style="border-radius: 8px; max-width:100%;height:auto;"  />

        
    </figure>


<p>I appreciate the efforts of people of Laoag to preserve and/or restore some of its old architecture, which supposedly is a blend of Spanish and Ilocano sensibilities. Whether this is by choice or by the fact that erecting new structures is costly, I didn&rsquo;t have the chance to know. I don&rsquo;t speak Ilocano, unfortunately, despite my wanting to. I could mimic a fragment of their accent, but that&rsquo;s about it. Thus, my interactions were limited to my Tagalog tongue.</p>

    <figure class="center" >
        <img src="/images/tfw11.jpeg"  alt="people gathering in front of the Capitol Building"   style="border-radius: 8px; max-width:100%;height:auto;"  />

        
            <figcaption class="center"  style="color: 297298;" >People gathered in front of the Capitol for some event</figcaption>
        
    </figure>


<p>Food is good. I brought home two kilograms of <em>bagnet</em> (deep fried pork belly, Ilocan&rsquo;s <em>chicharon</em>), which lasted us about a month. Natives of Ilocandia, if I may infer, are devotees of pork and vegetables. Who isn&rsquo;t?</p>

    <figure class="center" >
        <img src="/images/tfw12.jpeg"  alt="an intersection, a spire looms in the background"   style="border-radius: 8px; max-width:100%;height:auto;"  />

        
            <figcaption class="center"  style="color: 297298;" >People going to the gathering in front of the Capitol for some event</figcaption>
        
    </figure>


<hr>
<h2 id="cabanatuan-nueva-ecija">Cabanatuan, Nueva Ecija</h2>
<p>We went to a mall, everybody! One of the contractors offered lunch, and no one declined.</p>
<hr>
<h2 id="tarlac-city-tarlac">Tarlac City, Tarlac</h2>
<p>It&rsquo;s both hot and humid in the afternoon &ndash; typical weather in this region. Except it isn&rsquo;t. These were the last few days of a fairly cool climate, and after that, everything would either melt or burn or wither in summer heat. Here in Tarlac, it would be flames, figuratively, I hope. But for now, enjoy the sun when it isn&rsquo;t that warm yet.</p>
<hr>
<h2 id="lucena-city-quezon-province">Lucena City, Quezon Province</h2>
<p>We were received with plenty of plates of food before our inspection. Our timing couldn&rsquo;t be better: the P-Team there were celebrating their 30th Anniversary of Something, which seemed important, hence the buffet. After the work, we were invited again to partake in another set of food. It rained that afternoon. Even without umbrella, no cold nor flu befell me as I dared dash through the drizzle. Also worth noting: someone from the P-Team offered to buy me a big tin can of broas. I tried to pay him back, but he kept pushing the bills back to my palms, shaking his head, smiling.</p>
<hr>
<h2 id="bacolod-city">Bacolod City</h2>
<p>Is Bacolod the city of smiles? I think that&rsquo;s the tagline of another city. Bacolod burns its rubbish wherever it&rsquo;s convenient. Thrash-filled streets were no fun to walk on. What&rsquo;s worse is the perennial smoke from all the burning thrash. Some of their food is okay, though. We tried <a href="https://www.facebook.com/meisalmonhouse/">Mei&rsquo;s Salmon House</a>, an eat-all-you-can salmon-everything food place. Their fish, they say, is imported from Canada!</p>
<hr>
<h2 id="ozamis-city">Ozamis city</h2>
<p>The first waft of air when I deplaned smelled like provincial cow shit, familiar and strong as always. I am reminded of much simpler times from way back&hellip; It was a brief visit, as usual, because the rest of it was business-related, and you know I&rsquo;d drop that in a heartbeat. Much of Misamis Occidental breezed past me on a window, in an unruly car ride to&hellip;</p>
<hr>
<h2 id="dipolog-city">Dipolog City</h2>

    <figure class="center" >
        <img src="/images/tfw9.jpeg"  alt="view of sidewalk by some local elementary school"   style="border-radius: 8px; max-width:100%;height:auto;"  />

        
            <figcaption class="center"  style="color: 297298;" >1,837 kilometers from Rizal Park</figcaption>
        
    </figure>


<p>Here we settled. I chose <a href="https://www.agoda.com/gv-hotel-dipolog-city/hotel/dipolog-ph.html">GV Hotel</a> not for its outstanding services, which they don&rsquo;t have, nor for their polished facilities, which they also don&rsquo;t have. In fact, if you click that link, Agoda will tell you it&rsquo;s a one-star hotel. No, I chose GV Hotel because of its close proximity to our next business agenda in Zamboanga del Norte. Boulevard is also just several streets away. After lunch in <a href="https://www.tripadvisor.com.ph/Restaurant_Review-g659927-d8004943-Reviews-Grandma_s_Best-Dipolog_Zamboanga_del_Norte_Zamboanga_Peninsula_Mindanao.html">Grandma&rsquo;s Best</a>, we went to Dakak Beach Resort in&hellip;</p>
<hr>
<h2 id="dapitan-city">Dapitan City</h2>

    <figure class="center" >
        <img src="/images/tfw8.jpeg"  alt="view of a white-sand beach with a huge sign saying Dakak"   style="border-radius: 8px; max-width:100%;height:auto;"  />

        
            <figcaption class="center"  style="color: 297298;" >The only way to spend the afternoon: Beach!</figcaption>
        
    </figure>



    <figure class="center" >
        <img src="/images/tfw7.jpeg"  alt="view of a white-sand beach"   style="border-radius: 8px; max-width:100%;height:auto;"  />

        
            <figcaption class="center"  style="color: 297298;" >Well, not exactly. We were under the shade the whole 30 minutes we were here.</figcaption>
        
    </figure>



    <figure class="center" >
        <img src="/images/tfw5.jpeg"  alt="shade under a tree"   style="border-radius: 8px; max-width:100%;height:auto;"  />

        
            <figcaption class="center"  style="color: 297298;" >Proof of said shade. Also, name this tree.</figcaption>
        
    </figure>


<p>This whole leg was just a side trip, but a much needed one, if only to break away from work even for just a few hours. By the beach in &lsquo;Jalosjos Country&rsquo;, I got to see again the sea, my second time this year. Fine white sand met rubber soles.</p>

    <figure class="center" >
        <img src="/images/tfw6.jpeg"  alt="a cliff seen from the beach, surrounded by flora"   style="border-radius: 8px; max-width:100%;height:auto;"  />

        
            <figcaption class="center"  style="color: 297298;" >Layers in a Beach Picture (or, How Normies Do It With Smartphone Photography)</figcaption>
        
    </figure>



    <figure class="center" >
        <img src="/images/tfw4.jpeg"  alt="view of a mountainside by the beach?"   style="border-radius: 8px; max-width:100%;height:auto;"  />

        
            <figcaption class="center"  style="color: 297298;" >Not sure if that&#39;s still part of Jalosjos property</figcaption>
        
    </figure>


<p>After that, we&rsquo;re off to Rizal Shrine, about 10 kilometers away, a relatively short trip. The simple way of living of Pepe inspires me to do the same landscaping on our own residence in the future. We&rsquo;ll see&hellip; I only have a few pictures as souvenirs.</p>

    <figure class="center" >
        <img src="/images/tfw3.jpeg"  alt="a painting depicting Rizal treating his mother"   style="border-radius: 8px; max-width:100%;height:auto;"  />

        
            <figcaption class="center"  style="color: 297298;" >Rizal treating his mother. A very different painting from what I found online, that of Romeo Enriquez</figcaption>
        
    </figure>



    <figure class="center" >
        <img src="/images/tfw1.jpeg"  alt="an open nipa hut furnished with kitchen utensils"   style="border-radius: 8px; max-width:100%;height:auto;"  />

        
            <figcaption class="center"  style="color: 297298;" >Rizal&#39;s open kitchen</figcaption>
        
    </figure>



    <figure class="center" >
        <img src="/images/tfw2.jpeg"  alt="a raised nipa hut, octagonal in shape"   style="border-radius: 8px; max-width:100%;height:auto;"  />

        
            <figcaption class="center"  style="color: 297298;" >Rizal&#39;s raised octagonal clinic</figcaption>
        
    </figure>


<hr>
<p>At the time of writing, we are still in lockdown. The distance that we must only travel has been drastically reduced. Perhaps out of boredom we will document our homebound travels, so local in scope it can only be done for free; and blog about it.</p>
<p><code>-O)-</code></p>
]]></content>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>Comfort in Static</title>
            <link>/posts/comfort-static/</link>
            <pubDate>Wed, 01 Apr 2020 16:23:20 +0800</pubDate>
            
            <guid>/posts/comfort-static/</guid>
            <description>Durable and Affordable Radio  For years it has been a constant breakfast staple in our household the unique voice of Joe Taruc along with kapeng barako and pan de sal. Every day I would hear the program Pangunahing Balita and Damdaming Bayan in our kitchen/dining/sala area. According to Wikipedia, these shows are the longest running public affairs program. From the time I wake up to the time I need to leave the house, the radio is tuned in to DZRH.</description>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[
    <figure class="center" >
        <img src="/images/radio1.jpg"  alt="A plastic box with holes and dial sitting atop a banig"   style="border-radius: 8px; max-width:100%;height:auto;"  />

        
            <figcaption class="center"  style="color: 297298;" >Durable and Affordable Radio</figcaption>
        
    </figure>


<p>For years it has been a constant breakfast staple in our household the unique voice of Joe Taruc along with <em>kapeng barako</em> and <em>pan de sal</em>. Every day I would hear the program <em>Pangunahing Balita</em> and <em>Damdaming Bayan</em> in our kitchen/dining/sala area. According to Wikipedia, these shows are the longest running public affairs program. From the time I wake up to the time I need to leave the house, the radio is tuned in to DZRH. In some occasions, it&rsquo;s the classical station, owned by the same owner of DZRH. The blaring radio in the morning is a reminder that our father is home and having a dose of his news; or sometimes, I wonder, his dose of background noise every morning.</p>
<p>Last 12 January 2020, days after welcoming the new decade we were greeted with the phreatic eruption of Taal Volcano in Batangas. Taal Volcano is known for being a volcano within a volcano or a lake within a lake. We were 110 kilometers away from the eruption site but ashfall still descended on our humble abode. The eruption had forced evacuation for all residents living in 14km danger radius because the activity inside around Taal Volcano has not subsided. Earthquakes were felt and fissures appeared around the lake. Talk about starting your year with a blast. And anything could get worse. And it would.</p>
<p>When the eruption happened, I immediately check our supplies and if we had enough to create our go bags just incase something worst happens. I have seriously taken to heart the lessons that was taught during my fieldwork and trainings conducted during my stint in a government agency.</p>
<blockquote>
<p><strong>GO BAG:</strong> is an emergency preparedness that you pack in advance and an emergency kit. It should consists of supplies (medicine ,nonperishable food, potable water, clothes, blankets, tools: flashlight, radio, Swiss army knife) that will last for 72 hours (until help or first emergency responders come). The go bag should also house a copy of important paper items like birth certificate, passport and etc.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>We have secured the nonperishable goods but lacked the tools like radio and flashlight. Having move recently to a new place we really haven&rsquo;t been able to fully organized ourself. Good thing there are number of malls near our place. We decided to go to an appliance store in SM Masinag. They have decent selections of radios that would be in our price range. There weren&rsquo;t a lot of choices but there were a few decent ones. We had a budget of 500.00 pesos to 800.00 pesos. We went with the radio that looks durable and affordable. Our choice was a PENSONIC: Hybrid Radio.</p>

    <figure class="center" >
        <img src="/images/radio4.jpg"  alt="Back of the radio with labels and place for batteries"   style="border-radius: 8px; max-width:100%;height:auto;"  />

        
            <figcaption class="center"  style="color: 297298;" >Anatomy of Hybrid Radio</figcaption>
        
    </figure>



    <figure class="center" >
        <img src="/images/radio2.jpg"  alt="Side view of the plastic radio"   style="border-radius: 8px; max-width:100%;height:auto;"  />

        
            <figcaption class="center"  style="color: 297298;" >A.M. and F.M. Bandwidth</figcaption>
        
    </figure>


<p>A few days after buying the radio, we didnâ€™t immediately turned it on. I guess, Ohio is not a fan of morning news. I canâ€™t blame him because all you get are bad, overly sensationalized news. So I only tune in alone. Familiarizing myself with the power, volume, and tuner knobs on the side of the plastic radio. To power, you have to turn up and clockwise the power/volume knob, while another knob is used for scanning. The speaker produces a familiar humming static. It transports me back to another place and time.  Flashes of memories and feelings are made present when the static sound permeates the surrounding. Tested if the dial was moving and scanned all the stations in A.M. and F.M.</p>
<p>Besides the fact that we got it to  complete our go bag it is also our way to get news and entertainment. The radio for me serves as a gateway to access memories that brings me great comfort and nostalgic feelings. Back at a time where worries seem to be so distant, morning conversations and debates were part of the breakfast ritual, I am back in our round table nibbling on my <em>pan de sal</em> and savoring mg chocolate drink. A time where optimism thrives in my mind.</p>
<p>I tune in to the radio not only to listen to the news but also fill to the space with static that has given me great comfort. <code>-O)-</code></p>

    <figure class="center" >
        <img src="/images/radio3.jpg"  alt="Radio with its antenna out"   style="border-radius: 8px; max-width:100%;height:auto;"  />

        
            <figcaption class="center"  style="color: 297298;" >Another source of entertainment</figcaption>
        
    </figure>


]]></content>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>A Health(y) Discourse</title>
            <link>/posts/healthy-discourse/</link>
            <pubDate>Fri, 27 Mar 2020 19:09:11 +0800</pubDate>
            
            <guid>/posts/healthy-discourse/</guid>
            <description>Photo by Neil Thomas on Unsplash  We believe in a cooperative economy, especially now when we see how many of the modern day constructs that define how we exist could easily be waived due to COVID-19 pandemic. It only shows how many of these constructs are non-essential to human existence. Who knew that by keeping only whatâ€™s enough can maintain modern lives? In the long run, this is more sustainable than jump-starting (again) the gears of capitalism.</description>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[
    <figure class="center" >
        <img src="/images/nt.jpg"  alt="a hand statue propping up a tree"   style="border-radius: 8px; max-width:100%;height:auto;"  />

        
            <figcaption class="center"  style="color: 297298;" >Photo by Neil Thomas on Unsplash</figcaption>
        
    </figure>


<p>We believe in a cooperative economy, especially now when we see how many of the modern day constructs that define how we exist could easily be waived due to COVID-19 pandemic. It only shows how many of these constructs are non-essential to human existence. Who knew that by keeping only whatâ€™s enough can maintain modern lives? In the long run, this is more sustainable than jump-starting (again) the gears of capitalism.</p>
<p>This is not to say we endorse far-left state communism &ndash; far from it. Itâ€™s just that all our lives, we have relied on authorities for our lives â€“ from the food we eat to our health care system â€“ and where really has it lead us?</p>
<p>This current pandemic is all sorts of bad, and in order to <em>flatten the curve</em>, we are advised to stay at home away from crowds, and wash our hands with soap. As evidenced by many photos online, our collective confinement has cleared the skylines of many major cities, which is all sorts of good. That said, we donâ€™t mean to thank the pandemic for reducing global pollution, that would be myopic; rather, we use it as a lens with which to study the effects of our behavior and their impact on our environment, and of course ask, &ldquo;Do we really need a third rogue party to influence our (in)actions?&rdquo;</p>
<p>Everybody affects everyone, if that&rsquo;s still not obvious, regardless of geopolitical location, socioeconomic status, or whatever identifier you have for yourself. Each individual action ripples out, and has the possibility of gaining momentum as it reaches more people. Only if and when we agree to help one another can good things move forward at steady pace. We owe it to one another to be organized as this is a mutual benefit for all people concerned.</p>
<hr>
<h2 id="health-is-wealth">Health is wealth</h2>
<p>The best time to be thinking about good praxis is the time you are the healthiest, as this is also the time that you are most capable of enduring stress â€“ stress you will inevitably encounter should you choose to help others in these hard times. Each and everyone of us knows, or at least has some idea of, our own temperament. This is important to gauge for yourself, so youâ€™ll know how and when you can help others, setting expectations for yourself and for them.</p>
<p>We donâ€™t imply to preserve just yourself, though; rather, youâ€™re more capable of helping others when youâ€™re already in a relatively stable condition. We encourage you to evaluate some lifestyle choices you can make in order to keep yourself as healthy for as long as possible.</p>
<p>We have the capacity to go beyond the hoarding mentality that has been instilled in us by generations past. If and when we finally do that, we will begin to see that there is enough of everything for everyone.</p>
<p>In a profit-driven society, what then is our incentive to help one another?</p>
<p>It helps to borrow a great quote from Malcolm X to reframe the mindset:</p>
<blockquote>
<p><em>â€œWhen â€˜Iâ€™ is replaced with â€˜weâ€™, even illness becomes wellness.â€</em></p>
</blockquote>
<p>Donâ€™t flinch if it sounds cheesier than your mousetrap bait; it only means that as social creatures, we are, in many ways, responsible for the well-being of our neighbors (as we already said). The â€˜incentiveâ€™, then, is obtained in helping others enrich their lives, that in so doing, most likely, enriches us in turn. they would reciprocate. This is the nature of volunteerism, of developers contributing to open-source software, of editors editing Wikipedia entries for free, and other pro bono endeavors. Even insulin and penicillin was made available to the public un-patented.</p>
<p>Do what you can!</p>
<p>That is, help in whatever way you can. Small actions yield big benefits, especially when it&rsquo;s for the betterment of many people.</p>
<hr>
<h2 id="bonus">Bonus</h2>
<p>The following is a non-exhaustive list of plants that are considered <em>superfoods</em> because they: (a) can easily be grown and propagated with requiring basic knowledge and little effort; (b) are always available either on your nearest wet market or in the wilds of your backyard; (c) are packed with nutrients.</p>
<ol>
<li><a href="https://businessmirror.com.ph/2018/10/04/malunggay-the-countrys-vegetable-icon/">Malunggay</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=T3kWuSIFngQ">Kangkong</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.getroman.com/health-guide/this-is-how-garlic-can-do-your-body-good/">Garlic</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.livestrong.com/article/517905-health-benefits-of-alugbati/">Alugbati</a></li>
<li><a href="http://bpi.da.gov.ph/bpi/images/Production_guide/pdf/The%20KULITIS%20Plant.pdf">Kulitis</a></li>
</ol>
<p><code>-O)-</code></p>
]]></content>
        </item>
        
    </channel>
</rss>
