<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <channel>
        <title>Posts on Araw Seekers</title>
        <link>http://example.org/posts/</link>
        <description>Recent content in Posts on Araw Seekers</description>
        <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
        <language>en-us</language>
        <lastBuildDate>Wed, 10 Jul 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
        <atom:link href="http://example.org/posts/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
        
        <item>
            <title>The Imperfect Narrative of Repairing an iPod Classic 160GB</title>
            <link>http://example.org/posts/repair-ipod/</link>
            <pubDate>Wed, 10 Jul 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            
            <guid>http://example.org/posts/repair-ipod/</guid>
            <description>First, an Introduction Call me, for now, Ohio, one-half of the Araw Seekers. And in my opinion, repairing broken things needs a bit of technical skill to understand what one needs to do on a particular situation with the tools one has. Repairing also happens to be a noble undertaking for anyone who is looking into reducing the waste we send to our landfills. In this world filled with people who breaks things, a repair-person is in demand, nay, GOLD.</description>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<!-- wp:heading -->

<p><h2>First, an Introduction</h2>
<!-- /wp:heading --></p>

<!-- wp:paragraph {"align":"left"} -->

<p><p style="text-align:left">Call me, for now, Ohio, one-half of the Araw Seekers. And in my opinion, repairing broken things needs a bit of technical skill to understand what one needs to do on a particular situation with the tools one has. Repairing also happens to be a noble undertaking for anyone who is looking into reducing the waste we send to our landfills. In this world filled with people who breaks things, a repair-person is in demand, nay, GOLD.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>

<!-- wp:paragraph -->

<p><p>This is one of my current fascinations. While engineering school taught me how physical things behave the way they do, the programs there focused on the theoretical side of things. The tactility involved in reverse-engineering things, to me at least, is more rewarding. </p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>

<!-- wp:paragraph -->

<p><p>As a kid, I disassembled toy radios with a Philips screwdriver and examined the circuit board within, as if I understood each part. Of course, everything then looked foreign, but it was one of the few moments in life when I admired the Unknown <em>because</em>, not in spite of, its abstract layout. Much, much later, I would come to find out that circuit boards, and the parts within, serve a function in a device it is installed in. </p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>

<!-- wp:paragraph -->

<p><p>In one of his talks, the notorious astrophysicist Neil deGrasse Tyson encouraged parents to let their children mess around with their playthings, granted that they wouldn&rsquo;t get into hazardous situations. He meant that in order to begin the process of learning, one must be proud in their practice to break things apart, even if it&rsquo;s just for the sake of looking at their parts; and to have adults guide them doing so, not be preventing them just because it makes the house untidy.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>

<!-- wp:paragraph -->

<p><p>As years went by, the curiosity has lessened, because we, the practical adults, have too little time to be curious just for fun. Or that we have found fun in other exertions of effort. </p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>

<!-- wp:paragraph -->

<p><p>Today, anyone can begin learning how to repair broken stuff. If you think expertise matters, then do a quick search in YouTube for repair tutorials. Most of them are created by people enthused by the prospect of helping others repair their own things. If, you think the proper tools matter, why, yes, they do, but some of them can be borrowed from your friend or neighbor.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>

<!-- wp:heading -->

<p><h2>Now, the iPod</h2>
<!-- /wp:heading --></p>

<!-- wp:paragraph -->

<p><p>This recent fascination lead me to hound for broken things to practice my novice repair skills with. I had no specific rubric with which to refer to when it comes to what exact kinds of things to fix, but I guess the main driver would be, repairing it would bring its functionality back and add value (again) to life. </p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>

<!-- wp:paragraph -->

<p><p>In my search, I saw Isya&rsquo;s iPod tucked away in a drawer, unused, almost forgotten. I asked her immediately what was its problem.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>

<!-- wp:paragraph -->

<p><p>It wasn&rsquo;t turning on, even when we tried plugging it to a power source. She also vaguely recalled that she might have rolled over it. </p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>

<!-- wp:paragraph -->

<p><p>I remember watching a <a href="https://invidio.us/watch?v=SuTcavAzopg">Casey and Van Neistat video</a> that went viral in the early naught&rsquo;s, titled &ldquo;iPod&rsquo;s Dirty Secret&rdquo;. It exposed that &ldquo;iPOD&rsquo;S UNREPLACEABLE [sic] BATTERY LASTS ONLY 18 MONTHS&rdquo;. At the time, to refurbish the iPod with a bust battery, the owner would have to send it back to Apple&rsquo;s Customer Service and pay around US$ 250. At that price, why not just get a new one?</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>

<!-- wp:paragraph -->

<p><p>This business strategy isn&rsquo;t exclusive to Apple&rsquo;s iPods, nor to Apple, for that matter. In the time of Thomas Edison, incandescent light bulbs&rsquo; filament was changed from carbon to tungsten &ndash; the latter being thinner than the former, and thus cheaper to reproduce &ndash; so that selling them had become more profitable because of planned obsolescence. </p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>

<!-- wp:paragraph -->

<p><p>There are many other companies that continue to sell their products with planned obsolescence. This means that the product &ndash; in many of them, electronic device &ndash; is designed to break down after a few years of regular use. Worse, when they do break down, it&rsquo;s constructed to be difficult to open. They also don&rsquo;t share the repair manual. If one did manage to open it, the parts are either glued together, attached to the case with incompatible screws, or their replacements are hard to find.  </p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>

<!-- wp:paragraph -->

<p><p>&ldquo;Can I repair it?&rdquo; I asked Isya. </p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>

<!-- wp:paragraph -->

<p><p>Let there be silence.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>

<!-- wp:heading -->

<p><h2>Isya&rsquo;s iPod &ndash; an interstitial</h2>
<!-- /wp:heading --></p>

<!-- wp:paragraph -->

<p><p>When Isya&rsquo;s sister won grand prize for an art competition, she (the sister) gave Isya an iPod Classic (what is now known as 7th gen) as a gift. Although it was only recently that I found out about its origins, the sentimental value only reinforced the need for my restoring it. </p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>

<!-- wp:heading -->

<p><h2>What Happened Next</h2>
<!-- /wp:heading --></p>

<!-- wp:paragraph -->

<p><p> So, amid the lull between bid-thee-well and borrow, I managed to convince Isya to let me try to upgrade her iPod Classic. This was after I already did research on the matter, what parts to buy, what tools to pry it with, and so on.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>

<!-- wp:paragraph -->

<p><p>Starting out, it&rsquo;s important to have a guide one can work with, unless one has been gifted with wits to deal with a complex electronic device. My starting point for this project was <a href="https://invidio.us/watch?v=4AF1Pjbwc6c">Geek Detour&rsquo;s video</a>. It&rsquo;s informative as well as entertaining. Everson Siqueira, the channel&rsquo;s host, also details what he did wrong, so the viewers can learn from his mistakes.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>

<!-- wp:heading -->

<p><h2>The Repair Process</h2>
<!-- /wp:heading --></p>

<!-- wp:paragraph -->

<p><p>Here&rsquo;s the list of things that I bought online:</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>

<!-- wp:list -->

<p><ul><li><a href="https://www.iflash.xyz/store/iflash-quad/">iFlash-Quad microSD Adapter</a>. This Solid State Drive (SSD) would replace the old onboard Hard Disk Drive (HDD), requiring less battery usage while improving loading speed. </li><li> Special prying tool for iPod Classic. This is also listed in the iFlash store. </li><li>MicroSD Cards. Look for the info listed on iFlash site as to what cards would work well with the adapter. At the time of this writing, we bought two (2) pcs of Lexar 64GB microSD cards. There are two (2) remaining slots, which we might use some time in the future.</li><li><a href="https://www.ebay.ph/itm/Replacement-battery-for-ipod-classic-7th-gen-generation-160GB-650mAh-thin/223227260913">New Battery</a>. </li></ul>
<!-- /wp:list --></p>

<!-- wp:paragraph -->

<p><p>The original plan was to have the iPod up and running again before our first international trip together, scheduled on mid-June 2019. We would stock-pile on playlists and listen to them on the plane for the two-something hours of flight to Taipei. </p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>

<!-- wp:paragraph -->

<p><p>Of course, we junked that plan in quiet unison. The role of the iPod, while it has surfaced, had not been fully realized, not with its upgrade parts still not coming together. My reasons for not facing this project for some time now should be incredible, and some of them, familial in nature, <em>are</em>; however, it took a few more weeks past our Taiwan travel before I, a self-appointed repair-person, got to finally sit down with the tools and parts and do what I had been intending to do in months before. </p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>

<!-- wp:paragraph -->

<p><p>If we were to include in the process the time I had waited for the items to be delivered, then this whole fiasco lasted about three months, including the time I spent in lethargic limbo. Life happens, and sometimes I get less excited even on things that I am passionate about. </p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>

<!-- wp:paragraph -->

<p><p>Upgrading Isya&rsquo;s iPod turned out to be a success, of course, but as the title implies, the state in which I put it in now is below standard. Look:</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>

<!-- wp:gallery {"ids":[32,33,36,37]} -->

<p><ul class="wp-block-gallery columns-3 is-cropped"><li class="blocks-gallery-item"><figure><img src="https://arawseekers.files.wordpress.com/2019/07/20190710_113618.jpg" alt="" data-id="32" data-link="https://arawseekers.wordpress.com/20190710_113618/" class="wp-image-32"/></figure></li><li class="blocks-gallery-item"><figure><img src="https://arawseekers.files.wordpress.com/2019/07/20190710_113638.jpg" alt="" data-id="33" data-link="https://arawseekers.wordpress.com/20190710_113638/" class="wp-image-33"/></figure></li><li class="blocks-gallery-item"><figure><img src="https://arawseekers.files.wordpress.com/2019/07/20190710_113728.jpg" alt="" data-id="36" data-link="https://arawseekers.wordpress.com/20190710_113728/" class="wp-image-36"/></figure></li><li class="blocks-gallery-item"><figure><img src="https://arawseekers.files.wordpress.com/2019/07/20190710_113740.jpg" alt="" data-id="37" data-link="https://arawseekers.wordpress.com/20190710_113740/" class="wp-image-37"/></figure></li></ul>
<!-- /wp:gallery --></p>

<!-- wp:paragraph -->

<p><p>I can&rsquo;t figure out why there is an opposing force pushing on the back panel, preventing my totally closing it. I could brute-force it to close, but I reckon this might damage the LCD screen, or pierce the battery, or what-have-you. I&rsquo;d like to think  I did all the steps correctly, but Isya commented that it could be that the battery I used was an ill fit for the the iPod.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>

<!-- wp:paragraph -->

<p><p>A proper repair guy would retrace the steps he did to figure out what went wrong where, but I think troubleshooting is better saved for the future as a separate endeavor. </p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>

<!-- wp:paragraph -->

<p><p>But it isn&rsquo;t stupid if it works, right? This iPod lives on, then.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
]]></content>
        </item>
        
    </channel>
</rss>
