<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <channel>
        <title>🌞 Araw Seekers 🌞</title>
        <link>/</link>
        <description>Recent content on 🌞 Araw Seekers 🌞</description>
        <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
        <language>en-us</language>
        <copyright>Isya and Ohio</copyright>
        <lastBuildDate>Mon, 22 Jul 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
        <atom:link href="/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
        
        <item>
            <title>Posts</title>
            <link>/posts/</link>
            <pubDate>Tue, 03 Nov 2020 18:06:16 +0800</pubDate>
            
            <guid>/posts/</guid>
            <description></description>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[]]></content>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>Who solicits the solstice?</title>
            <link>/about/</link>
            <pubDate>Mon, 22 Jul 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            
            <guid>/about/</guid>
            <description>We, the Araw Seekers, are two different individuals, who one day decided to write the journey and exploration of our thoughts, musings, and actions. Published in the Internet to be archived and serve as reference in understanding and living our present. The expressions written, hopefully, may help others navigate their own future musings and adventures.
Araw is the Filipino term for the Sun. Seekers are people who seek (v.), which then means:  to try to find or discover by searching or questioning  to try to obtain  to try or attempt to go in search or quest of   Dedicated to those who hope, no matter how dark the night is, knowing that morning, preluded by dawn, always comes.</description>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>We, the Araw Seekers, are two different individuals, who one day decided to write the journey and exploration of our thoughts, musings, and actions. Published in the Internet to be archived and serve as reference in understanding and living our present. The expressions written, hopefully, may help others navigate their own future musings and adventures.</p>
<p><em>Araw</em> is the Filipino term for the Sun. </p>
<p><em>Seekers</em> are people who seek (v.), which then means:
 </p>
<ul>
<li>to try to find or discover by searching or questioning </li>
<li>to try to obtain </li>
<li>to try or attempt</li>
<li>to go in search or quest of </li>
</ul>
<p>Dedicated to those who hope, no matter how dark the night is, knowing that morning, preluded by dawn, always comes. The seekers consist of Isya and Ohio (two different individuals) who currently occupy the same space and breathes the same air.</p>
<hr>
<p>If you love reading books, why not visit our second-hand bookstore on Instagram? We regularly update the selection. Proceeds will directly benefit the owners, Pablo and Edgar (dog and cat, respectively).</p>
<p><strong>IG: instagram.com/petbookshelf</strong></p>
<hr>
<p>Currently, we don&rsquo;t have comments section on this site. We accept and read comments, praise, or constructive criticism you might have for us, but we would rather you post it to your own site and link back here.</p>
<p>If you would rather have a conversation, email us: <strong><a href="mailto:arawseekers@tuta.io">arawseekers@tuta.io</a></strong></p>
<p>Subscribe to our <a href="https://arawseeker.github.io/posts/index.xml">RSS feed</a>!</p>
]]></content>
        </item>
        
    </channel>
</rss>
