<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>🌞 Araw Seekers 🌞</title>
    <link>/</link>
    <description>Recent content on 🌞 Araw Seekers 🌞</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>Isya and Ohio</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 15 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Plants as Trash Deterrent?</title>
      <link>/posts/plants-deterrent/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/plants-deterrent/</guid>
      <description>A staple in both landscaping and urban planning is adding a natural element in an otherwise human-made environment. Depending on the budget, it could be a fountain to provide a water element; or it could be as simple as adding plants along sidewalks. In places all over, we have seen good and bad implementations of these natural elements, but the most common perhaps is the latter &amp;mdash; plants.
Exhibit A People have concluded that this plant box (and many others) is where to place their trash.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Many days meshing into a manifesto (of sorts)</title>
      <link>/posts/manifesto/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 19 Aug 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/manifesto/</guid>
      <description>THE FACTUAL PIECES here shall be made obvious when necessary, so try to make allowances for every entry. They say that when two opposite states of matter coexist at a single point in time, it&amp;rsquo;s believed to be in superposition unless an observer finds themself literate enough of the ways to approach such nuance. Accordingly, these statements are neither true nor false until someone (you, the observer?) comes along, and formulates a theory that we can together test.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Taiwan Trip, June 2019, (Part 2 of 2)</title>
      <link>/posts/taiwan-part2/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 28 Jul 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/taiwan-part2/</guid>
      <description>Have you read Part 1?
Day 3 We ate breakfast in McDo, the one near the place we stayed in, and it didn’t serve any local variant of Taiwan&#39;s food. It&#39;s all hamburgers, fried chicken, and sausage McNothin’. Some would say that eating at a known (read: exploitive capitalist) fast food chain, one that you also have in your country, is a disservice to the self to get to know the locals or their food, but that wasn’t our case.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Taiwan Trip, June 2019, (Part 1 of 2)</title>
      <link>/posts/taiwan-part1/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 21 Jul 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/taiwan-part1/</guid>
      <description>5W, 1H of it The last week of October 2018, Gab (Isya’s sister) and Merci (Isya’s mother) went to Taipei, Taiwan to attend Gab’s first international group exhibit. Aside from that, they took the trip as a break from their usual routines in Manila and Dumaguete.&amp;nbsp;
Their five-day stay in Taipei, Taiwan did not bring any actual “pasalubong” or take-home gifts, but they had a lot of stories and memorable experiences to share with us, me and Ohio.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Imperfect Narrative of Repairing an iPod Classic 160GB</title>
      <link>/posts/repair-ipod/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Jul 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/repair-ipod/</guid>
      <description>First, an Introduction Call me, for now, Ohio, one-half of the Araw Seekers. And in my opinion, repairing broken things needs a bit of technical skill to understand what one needs to do on a particular situation with the tools one has. Repairing also happens to be a noble undertaking for anyone who is looking into reducing the waste we send to our landfills. In this world filled with people who breaks things, a repair-person is in demand, nay, GOLD.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Who solicits the solstice?</title>
      <link>/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Jul 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/about/</guid>
      <description>We, the Araw Seekers, are two different individuals, who one day decided to write the journey and exploration of our thoughts, musings, and actions. Published in the Internet to be archived and serve as reference in understanding and living our present. The expressions written, hopefully, may help others navigate their own future musings and adventures.
Araw is the Filipino term for the Sun. Seekers are people who seek (v.), which then means:</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>